<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[]]></title>
  <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-12T00:44:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brent Wejrowski]]></name>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marcuse and the Liquidation of Art]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/13/marcuse-and-the-liquidation-of-art.html"/>
    <updated>2017-06-13T23:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/13/marcuse-and-the-liquidation-of-art</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post I shared how Marcuse describes art and what it does and here I want to speak a bit more to what it had become. His section on art, literature, and culture, was just an example of how the industrialized society was transformed through technology to become, as he says, one dimensional.</p>

<p>Art previously had taken a stance of contrast to the established order of things and, with new technological advancements and a new kind of society, became hijacked, used as a form of domination. It no longer creates a sense of alienation that allow someone to step out of their present circumstances and look for something new. They became subsumed into this change that was happening, this new way of technological and administrative domination that creates a one dimensionality. It&rsquo;s purpose is to be sold, used for immediate gratification, used to entertain. It doesn&rsquo;t generate conscious reflection, or provocation, it generates submission. Art, literature, cultural values—real cultural values that had a an actual meaning—became liquidated and sold off.</p>

<blockquote><p>Today&rsquo;s novel feature is the flattening out of the antagonism between culture and social reality through the obliteration of the oppositional, alien, and transcendent elements in the higher culture by virtue of which it constituted another dimension of reality. This liquidation of two-dimensional takes place not through the denial and rejection of the &ldquo;cultural values,&rdquo; but through their wholesale incorporation into the established order, through their reproduction and display on a massive scale.
In fact, they serve as instruments of social cohesion. The greatness of a free literature and art, the ideals of humanism, the sorrows and joys of the individual, the fulfillment of the personality are important items in the competitive struggle between East and West. They speak heavily against the present forms of communism, and they are daily administered and sold. The fact that they contradict the society which sells them does not count. Just as people know or feel that advertisements and political platforms must not be necessarily true or right, and yet hear and read them and even let themselves be guided by them, so they accept the traditional values and make them part of their mental equipment. If mass communications blend together harmoniously, and often unnoticeably, art, politics, religion, and philosophy with commercials, they bring these realms of culture to their common denominator—the commodity form. The music of the soul is also the music of salesmanship. Exchange value, not truth value counts. On it centers the rationality of the status quote, and all alien rationality is bent to it. As the great words of freedom and fulfillment are pronounced by campaigning leaders and politicians, on the screens and radios and stages, they turn into meaningless sounds which obtain meaning only in the context of propaganda, business, discipline, and relaxation.
Herbert Marcuse / One Dimensional Man</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marcuse and Art as Subversion]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/12/marcuse-and-art-as-subversion.html"/>
    <updated>2017-06-12T23:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/12/marcuse-and-art-as-subversion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Herbert Marcuse has a similar perspective on art to the quote I shared in the previous post, except framed in very different, very intense, context. The previous concept was that art was essentially linked to life, understanding of life and involved clarification and interpretation. It reminded me of a chapter in Herbert Marcuse&rsquo;s One Dimensional Man where he writes about art and culture. Nearly every page of the entire book could be mulled over for quite some time, but I will just share this one particular piece.</p>

<p>One-Dimensional Man was written in 1964 and is a critical look at the effects of an industrialized and technological society, and Marcuse in this particular chapter shows the effects in relation to culture, art, and literature. What art once was, it no longer is. It&rsquo;s previous position had been transformed and consumed by this new way of life. It&rsquo;s essence was, as Zettl said in the previous post, to clarify and interpret existence, and for Marcuse it was this but even more—a subversion of the dominant society. Zettl pointed to an essential relation art has to life, and Marcuse gives it a more specific definition.</p>

<p>Marcuse speaks of art as being essentially a critical tool of negation, a subversive force that shows the world for what it is. It speaks truth through its content, showing the reality that we live in through vivid and intensified forms. It&rsquo;s not just art for arts sake, for beauty&rsquo;s sake, or for whatever might come of it, but it&rsquo;s art that speaks truth, and evokes new possibilities because it shows what is not, what is lacking, and what could be. To see new possibilities you must be able to label things as they are, to see what can be different. And this is what art, or art, literature, and culture, as he explains, lost with technological advancements. His stance brings a more pertinent depth to the concept of art that I very much appreciate, and it stuck with me.</p>

<blockquote><p>Prior to the advent of this cultural reconciliation, literature and art were essentially alienation, sustaining and protecting the contradiction—the unhappy consciousness of the divided world, the defeated possibilities, the hopes unfulfilled, and the promises betrayed. They were a rational, cognitive force, revealing a dimension of man and nature which was repressed and repelled in reality. Their truth was in the illusion evoked, in the insistence on creating a world in which the terror of life was called up and suspended—mastered by recognition. This is the miracle of the chef-d'oevre; it is the tragedy, sustained to the last, and the end of tragedy—its impossible solution. To live one&rsquo;s love and hatred, to live that which one is means defeat, resignation, and death. The crimes of society, the hell that man has made for man become unconquerable cosmic forces.
The tension between the actual and the possible is transfigured into an insoluble conflict, in which reconciliation is by grace of the oevre as form: beauty as the &ldquo;promesse de bonheur.&rdquo; In the form of the oevre, the actual circumstances are placed in another dimension where the given reality shows itself as that which it is. Thus it tells the truth about itself; its language ceases to be that of deception, ignorance, and submission. Fiction calls the facts by their name and their reign collapses; fiction subverts everyday experience and shows it to be mutilated and false. But art has this magic power only as the power of negation. It can speak its own language only as long as the images are alive which refuse and refute the established order.
Herbert Marcuse / One Dimensional Man</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Art: Experience Clarified, Intensified, and Interpreted]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/11/art-and-experience.html"/>
    <updated>2017-06-11T23:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2017/06/11/art-and-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I came across an idea of art that I enjoyed. I haven&rsquo;t ever held a particular definition of art, although for me, especially looking at certain works of art, it can be quite ambiguous, almost meaningless, or often times just confusing. In the book Sight Sound Motion, which is a media aesthetics textbook I had laying around from college that I started reading, Herbbert Zettle begins the book by framing it within this idea of art being firmly linked with life and our attempt to understand it. He even says that art seems to be necessary to life a life with quality and dignity. What I liked about it was that it gave an angle to art and what art could be.</p>

<blockquote><p>The philosopher Irwin Edman pioneered a new aesthetic concept more than half a century ago that stresses the close connection between art and life. He wrote: &ldquo;So far from having to do merely with statues, pictures, symphonies, art is the name for that whole process of intelligence by which life, understanding its own conditions, turns these into the most interesting or exquisite account.&rdquo; This process presupposes that life is given &ldquo;line and composition&rdquo; and that the experience is clarified, intensified, and interpreted. &ldquo;To effect such an intensification and clarification of experience,&rdquo; Edman says, &ldquo;is the province of art.&rdquo;
Herbbert Zettle / Sight, Sound, Motion</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 7, Reverence for Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/12/15/philosophy-of-civilization-pt7.html"/>
    <updated>2014-12-15T23:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/12/15/philosophy-of-civilization-pt7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reverence for Life. I could leave it at that and be satisfied, because I find the phrase immediately gratifying. And it seems to sum up so
many things so well. But I will attempt, anyways, to explain more of what Schweitzer means by this.</p>

<!-- <img alt="Albert Schweitzer" title="Albert Schweitzer's Philosophy of Civilization (1924)" src="/assets/images/schweitzer-looking.jpg" class="alignright" width="300" /> -->


<p>Ethics. Compassion. Valuing life&mdash;all of life, no matter how small or seemingly insignificant. That is what Schweitzer is aiming for. That is what he believes is necessary for civilization. We must get to a place where this is a necessity of thought, not just an occasional stirring. To get beyond a dogmatic formula where rules are pitted against one another, where conviction for ethics is neglected. Beyond a utilitarian or economical conception of ethics based on end or gain, where ethics looks for justification. Where each of us is grounded in valuing, preserving, and upholding life in whatever way possible and feel the responsibility within us to do it in whatever way we can. How do I get to a place where I remember that my life is precious, that life is precious, and yours is just as much as mine is?</p>

<p>There is something within the nature of our existence that gives us this. It is perhaps the most basic fact that knowledge can lead us to. It is not even dependent on thought, though thought always comes back to it, even starts in it: it is our existence. It is the mysterious urge that each one of us is born with, an urge towards life&mdash;our will-to-live. I am alive and I want to be alive. I feel the life within me and see life around me and am inspired by that. I need no justification for it. I move around because I mysteriously have some sort of urge to move about in this world. Where it came from, I do not know&mdash;it&rsquo;s certainly not a given. What it means, I cannot tell. I simply live and want to live. I am thrown upon this world will an inexplicable forward urging will-to-live. Within this I have an inherent reverence for life within me, as I manifest this universal Will-to-live.</p>

<p>Schweitzer wants to cut the ties with interpretations of the world. The will-to-live, when it begins to think, gets pressed upon knowledge that Schweitzer says is without exception, pessimistic. It cannot be reconciled with knowledge. It lives in a world where it continues to move despite being in constant struggle with suffering and pain, with which it struggles until the day it dies. And the only thing that keeps it from giving into the pessimism which it finds, is an inherent repulsiveness to that thought. Knowledge brings us these facts, and if it is honest, perhaps only leads us back to this mystery. Previous thought had attempted to reconcile these and find some sort of explanation for this, but Schweitzer wants to ground ethics once and for all upon this will-to-live and separate it from interpretation of the world, because this will-to-live within us, this reverence for life that we have, can stand on its own.</p>

<p>This reverence for life becomes a sort of mystical dedication to this Will that manifests itself within us, to Being. Mysticism, Schweitzer says is what any world-view, if it is to satisfy thought, must begin with. But it must not be an abstract dedication to some Absolute, which becomes a death to ethics. It is an elemental mysticism, a mysticism of reality. When we devote ourselves to this infinite Being which manifests itself in infinite ways, I find meaning, Schweitzer says. I devote myself to life through this reverence for life. It becomes expansive, reaching beyond my own existence. I find that my life is valuable, that all life which we are all steeped within is valuable. And if I were honest, if I have my eyes open, I know that my life and my will, and that every will, is at odds with one another, and that my existence moves forward at the expense of others. Because of this I attempt, in whatever way I can find within me to dedicate myself to uphold life.</p>

<p>Here I will let Schweitzer speak some final words:</p>

<blockquote><p>A man is truly ethical only when he obeys the compulsion to help all life which he is able to assist, and shrinks from injuring anything that lives. He does not ask how far this or that life deserves one&rsquo;s sympathy as being valuable, nor beyond that, whether and to what degree it is capable of feeling. Life as such is sacred to him. He tears no leaf from a tree, plucks no flower, and takes care to crush no insect. If in summer he is working by lamplight, he prefers to keep the window shut and breathe a stuffy atmosphere rather than see one insect after another fall with singed wings upon his table&hellip;</p>

<p>If he walks on the road after a shower and sees an earthworm which has strayed on to it, he bethinks himself that it must get dried up in the sun, if it does not return soon enough to ground into which it can burrow, so he lifts it from the deadly stone surface, and puts it on the grass. If he comes across an insect which has fallen into a puddle, he stops a moment in order to hold out a leaf or a stalk on which it can save itself.</p>

<p>He is not afraid of being laughed at as sentimental. It is the fate of every truth to be a subject for laughter until it is generally recognized. Once it was considered folly to assume that man of color were really men and ought to be treated as such, but the folly has become an accepted truth. Today it is thought to be going too far to declare that constant regard for everything that lives, down to the lowest manifestations of life, is a demand made by rational ethics. The time is coming, however, when people will be astonished that mankind needed so long a time to learn to regard thoughtless injury to life as incompatible with ethics. (pg. 311)</p>

<p>No one must shut his eyes and regard as non-existent the sufferings of which he spares himself the sight. Let no one regard as light the burden of his responsibility. While so much ill-treatment of animals goes on, while the moans of thirsty animals in railway trucks sound unheard, while so much brutality prevails in our slaughter-houses, while animals have to suffer in our kitchens painful death from unskilled hands, while animals have to endure intolerable treatment from heartless men, or are left to the cruel play of children, we all share the guilt&hellip;</p>

<p>We must never let ourselves become blunted. We are living in truth, when we experience these conflicts more profoundly. The good conscious is an invention of the devil&hellip;</p>

<p>The ethics of reverence for life guard us from letting each other believe through our silence that we no longer experience what, as thinking men, we must experience. They prompt us to keep each other sensitive to what distress us, and to talk and act together, just as the responsibility we feel moves us, and without any feeling of shyness. They make us join in keeping on the look-out for opportunities of bringing some sort of help to animals, to make up for the great misery which men inflict on them, and thus to step for a moment out of the incomprehensible horror of existence (pg. 319)</p>

<p>Reverence for life is an inexorable creditor! If it finds anyone with nothing to pledge but a little time and a little leisure, it lays an attachment on these&hellip;
They demand that everyone of us in some way and with some object shall be a human being for human beings&hellip; Open your eyes and look for a human being, or some work devoted to human welfare, which needs from someone a little time or friendliness, a little sympathy, or sociability, or labour. There may be a solitary or an embittered fellow-man, an invalid or an inefficient person to whom you can be something. Perhaps it is an old person or a child. Or some good work needs volunteers who can offer a free evening, or run errands&hellip;. Search, then for some investment for your humanity, and do not be frightened away if you have to wait, or be taken on trial. And be prepared for disappointments. But in any case, do not be without some secondary work in which you give yourself as man to men. It is marked out for you, if you only truly will to have it&hellip;</p>

<p>Thus do the true ethics speak to those who have only a little time and a little human nature to give. Well will it be with them if they listen, and are preserved from becoming stunted natures because they have neglected this devotion of self to others&hellip;</p>

<p>But let neither judge the other. The destinies of men have to be decided in a thousand ways in order that the good may become actual. What he has to bring as an offering is the secret of each individual. But one with another we have all to recognize that our existence reaches its true value only when we experience in ourselves something of the truth of the saying: &ldquo;He that loseth his life shall find it.&rdquo; (pg. 323)</p></blockquote>

<p>There is so much more. I could really quote the entire book. But I will share one final quote, the last words of the book, that gets back to the idea that this attitude of reverence for life was&mdash;despite perhaps sounding vague or general&mdash;he believed, the only complete ethic.</p>

<blockquote><p>Kant published, with the title <em>Towards Perpetual Peace</em>, a work containing rules which were to be observed with a view to lasting peace whenever treaties of peace were concluded. It was a mistake. Rules for treaties of peace, however well intentioned and however ably drawn up, can accomplish nothing. Only such thinking as establishes the sway of the mental attitude of reverence for life can bring to mankind perpetual peace.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 6, Ethics and Resignation to Knowledge]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/12/07/philosophy-of-civilization-pt6.html"/>
    <updated>2014-12-07T19:33:28-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/12/07/philosophy-of-civilization-pt6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So if you wanted to come up with some sort of foundation for ethics, what would it be? Is there any way you could explain it? Can you explain altruism? Is there a principle behind it, a thought, an idea behind ethics or morality? How would attempt to explain why one should be ethical, moral, or kind even? History has given many different answers to this but Schweitzer says in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Philosophy-Civilization-Albert-Schweitzer/dp/0879754036">The Philosophy of Civilization</a> that they continually fall from one paradox to another and have failed to give us any sort of firm foundation. He says that looking back, the only thing we can gain from the history of ethics is &ldquo;a certain amount of clearness about the problem of ethics.&rdquo; They were, he says, attempting to ground it out of what they knew about the world, through their knowledge, through their world-view. He says we need to separate any knowledge we have of the world from our ethics. Resign to knowledge when it comes to ethics because ethical action is illogical and can stand, ultimately, on no interpretation of the world but only out of one&rsquo;s inward impulse. It cannot come out of some systematic interpretation, and it&rsquo;s only firm foundation is out of one&rsquo;s own inner reflection stemming from one&rsquo;s own life.</p>

<blockquote><p>Anyone who undertakes the voyage to true ethics must be prepared to be carried round and round in the whirlpool of the irrational. (pg. 292)</p>

<p>In the old rationalism reason undertook to investigate the world. In the new it has to take as its task the attaining to clarity about the will-to-live which is in us. Thus we return to an elemental philosophizing which is once more busied with questions of world- and live-view as they directly affect men, and seeks to give a safe foundation to, and keep alive, the valuable ideas which we find in ourselves.</p>

<p>Man must finally be content to force himself to acceptance of the ethically expansive life-affirmation, merely because he feels it to be the only things which is capable of making life valuable. (pg. 258)</p>

<p>It is certain further that true ethics are always subjective, that they have an irrational enthusiasm as the very breath of their life. (pg. 299)</p></blockquote>

<p>First of all, why the obsession with Ethics? Well, one of his first conclusions, one of his main questions and purposes in this book is to find out what civilization is, or is built on. He says society needs ethics. Civilization thrives when it is ethical, when the aim is general prosperity for everyone, where the struggle for existence is lessened, and where each individual is valued. The lack of ethics, or at least the lack of a real living ethic, was what he believed was driving civilization to its demise. One is needed that dealt not simply with society at large but with person to person, personality to personality, with human to human relationships, and not only that, but to all of life.</p>

<blockquote><p>Only in proportion as the prevalent philosophy is world- and life-affirming and at the same time ethical, do we find ideals of civilization put forward and kept influential in the habits of thought of individuals and of society. (pg. 91)</p></blockquote>

<!-- > The fundamental commandment of ethics... is that we cause no suffering to any living creature, not even the lowest.... -->


<blockquote><p>The criterion of a real code of ethics is whether it allows their full rights to the problems of personal morality and of the relation of man to man, problems with which we are concerned every day and every hour, and by means of which we must become ethical personalities. (pg. 151)</p></blockquote>

<p>Ethics had many different motivations, but it seemed to be losing it&rsquo;s ground, and becoming more and more out of touch, even,  unethical. Many explanations, when led to their conclusion, Schweitzer thought, did not lead to the ethical. Others had lost touch with reality. And others didn&rsquo;t have any foundation against the pessimistic and inexplicable suffering found in the world.</p>

<p>For example, many have explained ethics through ego, through the idea of self-preservation, or one&rsquo;s own happiness or pleasure. Maybe ethics is simply a way of getting along with others so that I can move forward in this world and survive. But, as much as these may lead to a bit of ethical action, they only lead there insofar as something is gained for one&rsquo;s self. They go no further than that, and thus aren&rsquo;t all that ethical, or at least do not have the type of ethic that Schweitzer is looking for. They are more self serving, and deceive us from any sort of guilt and outward impulse.</p>

<p>Others had explained ethics as an invention of society&mdash;that in order for society to work it needed to create ethical values to keep people in line in order to work together. This again, though, makes more of a utilitarian ethic, abstracting the ethical from reality. It serves the collective progress more than giving meaning and value to individuals, and forces an ethic upon people from above, rather than allowing it to flow from within, taking away from conviction and even personalities.</p>

<p>A similar sort of abstraction happens in Kant, who had tried to build ethics upon a universal principle. Schweitzer calls it his &ldquo;empty imperative.&rdquo; He points out that Kant (as well as many others) had viewed morality and ethics as consisting in static universal laws which end up being not quite ethical. They end up dealing more with abstract ideals and principles than the world in front of us, being more supra-ethical than ethical. Ethics need to have, he says, an empirical ground, dealing with the material here and now rather than what ends up being a cold relation to some principle. There is something empty, something robotic, about morality, or kindness, coming from a duty that I must be kind, that I must follow some ethical universal. Rules and principles can detach us from reality and bind us to follow them for our own gain. To appeal to a law or principle can lead to injustice rather than justice and human dignity. They perhaps distract us more than ground us, and detract us from something much more fundamental and meaningful.</p>

<blockquote><p>According to Nietzsche, accepted ethics are deficient in veracity, because the conceptions of good and evil which they put into circulation do not spring out of man&rsquo;s reflection on the meaning of his life, but have been invented in order to keep individuals useful to the majority. The weak proclaim that sympathy and love are good, because that is to their advantage. Thus led astray, all men try to force themselves to the opinion that they fulfill the highest destiny of their existence by self-sacrifice and the devotion of their lives to others. But this opinion never becomes a real inward conviction. They live out their lives without any thought of their own as to what makes life valuable. They join the crowd in praising the morality of humility and self-sacrifice as the true morality, but they do not really believe in it. They feel self-assurance to be what is natural, and act accordingly without admitting the fact to themselves. They do not question the general ethical prestige of humility and self-sacrifice; they help to maintain it, from fear that individuals stronger than themselves might become dangerous to them, if this method of taming men were abandoned&hellip;  the ethics of humility and self-sacrifice do as a matter of principle avoid engaging in a clear and practical discussion with reality. (pg. 244)</p></blockquote>

<p>Nietzsche and others started pointing out these failures and begun attempting to ground ethics on more elemental impulses. This, Schweitzer says, ethics needed. And this was bringing ethics closer to a more firm foundation. But not quite. There were two main problems with many of these. Either they were not yet giving up their interpretation, or they had nothing to keep them from completely resigning to life itself in the face of pessimism.</p>

<p>The western world had mainly interpreted life through what Schweitzer calls an optimistic-ethical point of view&mdash;an assumption that there is a general purposiveness to the universe that leads to progressive perfection. Schweitzer wants ethics with an optimistic-ethical, life-affirming, <em>impulse</em>, but believes the western optimistic-ethical <em>interpretation</em> of the world is bankrupt. It assumed automatic progress, that knowledge could only lead to better and better, but befooled us to escape the suffering around us, concealing the pessimism behind it. He says the facts were pressing up against it. Knowledge hadn&rsquo;t led it much of anywhere. It had only sidetracked it, even blinded it. There was an irony in the fact that aeroplanes could carry men through the air, over hunger and pillaging below. Schweitzer says we need to give up our world-view and wholly separate our world-view from ethics, and adapt ourselves to the facts. Our knowledge gives us no answer to the meaning of the world, nor towards ethics, nor gives us anything life-giving that is able to stand against the pessimism that surrounds us in nature.</p>

<blockquote><p>Our age is striking out unmeaning in every direction like a fallen horse in the traces. It is trying with external measures and new organization to solve the difficult problems with which it has to deal, but all in vain. The horse cannot get on its feet again till it is unharnessed and allowed to get its head up. (pg. 271)</p>

<p>The hopelessness of the attempt to find the meaning of life within the meaning of the universe is shown first of all by the fact that in the course of nature there is no purposiveness to be seen in which the activities of men, and of mankind as a whole, could in any way intervene. On one of the smaller among the millions of heavenly bodies there have lived for a short space of time human beings&hellip;. We are entirely ignorant of what significance we have for the earth. How much less then may we presume to try to attribute to the infinite universe a meaning which has us for its object, or which can be explained in terms of our existence!</p>

<p>It is not, however merely the huge disproportion between the universe and man which makes it impossible for us&hellip;. Any such attempt is made useless beforehand by the fact that we fail to succeed in discovering any general purposiveness in the course of nature. Whatever we do find of purposiveness in the world is never anything but an isolated instance&hellip; . [N]ature does sometimes act  purposively in a magnificent way. But in no way does she ever seem intent on uniting these instances of purposiveness which are directed to single objects into a collective purpose&hellip; . She is wonderfully creative force, and at the same time senselessly destructive force. We face her absolutely perplexed. What is full of meaning within the meaningless, the meaningless within what is full of meaning: that is the essential nature of the universe.</p>

<p>European thought has tried to ignore these elemental certainties. It can do so no longer, and it is of no use to try. The facts have silently produced their consequences. While the optimistic-ethical world-view is still current among us as a dogma, we no longer possess the ethical world- and life-affirmation which should result from it. Perplexity and pessimism have taken possession of us without our admitting the fact. There remains, therefore, nothing for us to do but confess that we understand nothing of the world, and are surrounded by complete enigmas.</p>

<p>Life attracts us, they say, with a thousand expectations, and fulfils hardly one of them&hellip;. Unrest, disappointment and pain are our lot in the short span of time which lies between our entrance on life and our departure from it&hellip; . Our existence is at the mercy of meaningless happenings and can be brought to an end by them at any moment&hellip; . Every thinking human being makes acquaintance with this thought. We let it take a deeper hold of us than we suspect from one another, as indeed we are all more oppressed by the riddles of existence than we allow others to notice. (pg. 279)</p></blockquote>

<p>So, says Schweitzer, we have to abandon the previous ways we&rsquo;ve attempted to come to ethics. We have to admit to our lack of knowledge and come towards ethics through a resignation to knowledge. Knowledge will not give us any meaning of the world, and it will be forever incomplete. And so we resign to it. Ethics is irrational. And the only true conviction and grounding for it comes from our own subjective reflection and impulse.  How do you give ethics any sort of grounding without being relative? What do you base it on, if anything? What is left that gives us this impulse? And is there anything that helps us face the suffering and enigmas we find around us? Schweitzer says it is this: our own will-to-live, our own inner manifestation of reverence for life.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 5, The Individual and society and a bit of Hegel]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/08/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt5.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-24T17:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/08/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the next few posts I&rsquo;m going to go over a few main points of what Schweitzer builds into his sort of proposal, or his ethic, or his way out. There is so much good stuff in this book it is hard to strip so much out but I&rsquo;m going to try to touch on some of his main points. Here I want to share something he brings up again and again about individuals and society, and relate/contrast it to some ideas in Hegel.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/rage_evil_empire.jpg" class="alignright" width="250" /></p>

<blockquote><p>The collapse of civilization has come about through ethics being left to society. A renewal of it is possible only if ethics become once more the concern of thinking human beings, and if individuals seek to assert themselves in society as ethical personalities. In proportion as we secure this, society will become an ethical, instead of the purely natural, entity, which it is by origin. Previous generations have made the terrible mistake of idealizing society as ethical. We do our duty to it by judging it critically, and trying to make it, so far as possible, more ethical. (p. 328)</p></blockquote>

<p>Schweitzer points to a basic conflict between society and individuals. This tension is seen not only by looking back on history, but it is a sort of fundamental one.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Georg_Wilhelm_Friedrich_Hegel-200.jpg" width="200" class="alignleft" />
Hegel puts interesting words to this conflict in Phenomenology of Spirit. It&rsquo;s a bit abstract, but if you can track with it, it gives some interesting perspective on this.</p>

<p>To have understanding we need to be able to distinguish between things. We give things names, and by doing so, we create separations in our mind. It allows us to reason with things. We can think about one thing and relate it to another. Doing this is perhaps what allows us to think about&hellip; well, anything. But, by doing this and by making and having these separations, you end up not including something else (e.g. the words society and individual).</p>

<p>We do this with external things in order to reason with them, but we also do this with ourselves. And this is what Hegel calls consciousness, which builds into what he calls the &ldquo;Spirit&rdquo; (also &ldquo;mind&rdquo;). A spirit, is something that has, or is out for, self-certainty. The forming of a consciousness, the forming of an individual, the forming of any idea really, is this distinguishing process of this and that, I and another etc. And a spirit (as I understood it) can come from anything—a person, group, language, idea—that does this. Once a word is formed, for example, and it leaves a person&rsquo;s mouth, it floats off and becomes its own sort of spirit, flies away and, just through the simple fact that there formed a word, or words, or concept around something, it begins to assert itself, and in a strange way take on its own spirit, out for it&rsquo;s own self-certainty by the fact that it simply exists. So there&rsquo;s a tension—a simple tension created simply by the naming and having ideas formed around certain concepts, but also through a struggle of a thing or person or group to keep or retain it&rsquo;s own sort of existence and certainty about itself.</p>

<p>There is a simple and natural side of this that happens with us because we all have different perspectives, and there is also a more sort of dysfunctional side of this. In a natural sense, I have my own perspective which I make decisions from, and my own self to protect, as does any other person or being or in a more abstract sense idea/group, which causes these to clash. So just through individuals having their own lens they look through, or a group having its own name or idea it stands by, there&rsquo;s going to be an ongoing difference/clash, which is normal. And in the more dysfunctional sense, as a person is maturing (or in Hegel, coming to more full consciousness) he often struggles to find himself. One can find a need to either exert himself over others and take advantage of others because he see the world only for himself or needs to gain more of a sense of self, or if a person does not see himself as his own person, he may latch onto an idea or another person because he doesn&rsquo;t see himself as his own person. You can see this perhaps in the whole &ldquo;opposites attract&rdquo; thing, or perhaps in a more intense way in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Codependency">codependent</a> relationships, or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroses#Horney.27s_theory">neurosis</a>, or even with charismatic leaders and the odd way large groups of people get magnetized by them. This conflict is part of Hegel&rsquo;s famous Master/Slave dialect, which also takes other forms throughout Phenomenology.</p>

<p>There interestingly comes a point where Hegel talks about this ideal where there is no longer this struggle for an individual or a spirit to assert itself, but understands it&rsquo;s relation to the world, that it works not just for-itself, but for-others, in more interdependence, or I think more precisely a unity.</p>

<p>Could you have society be both for itself and for it&rsquo;s members? Made for, by, and on behalf of it&rsquo;s members? Perhaps that is the goal. And I think in Hegel this is more of an understanding than an actuality. There is always a tension here. There is always a &ldquo;force,&rdquo; Hegel says, or back-and-forth between the two. By definition, by naming a society or any other collective group, its purpose ends up being for the collective, it ends up not including the individual—or if it does it is only supra-individual, it&rsquo;s above the individual. By simply having a name, it&rsquo;s concerned for something bigger than the individuals that it&rsquo;s supposed to contain. Even if it&rsquo;s &ldquo;concerned&rdquo; for the individual there is still a continual and constant tension between the two, even if ever so slightly.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t necessarily need that Hegelian explanation to see the tension, but I think it&rsquo;s interesting to look at it in those terms—to see it as a very fundamental one.</p>

<p>Schweitzer never actually mentions Hegel when he repeatedly makes a point about this conflict, or about the importance of the individuals own conviction when it comes to ethics. This is probably because Hegel ends up building this conflict ultimately into his idea of Spirit which, as others have criticized him for, may be more about the continual progress of history through thesis/antithesis than anything else. Schweitzer actually criticizes Hegel for this obsession for progress, as Hegel and other idealists like him were perhaps part of this problem which Schweitzer saw before him.</p>

<blockquote><p>He is the creator of that confident feeling for reality with which Europe staggered into the second half of the nineteenth century without becoming aware that ethics have at some point or another been left behind&hellip;. In Hegel originates the spirit which borrows its ideals empirically from reality and believes in the progress of humanity more than it labours to promote it. He stands on the bridge of an ocean liner and explains to the passengers the wonders of the machinery in the vessel that is carrying them, and the mysteries of the calculation of its course. But he gives no thought to the necessary maintenance of the fires under the boilers. Hence the speed gradually diminishes until the vessel comes at last to a standstill. It no longer obeys the helm, and becomes a plaything of the gales. (p. 220)</p></blockquote>

<p>The maintenance and thriving of progress and civilization, Schweitzer believed, was ethics, and ethics that sprang from basic individual conviction, not by declamation from a group. This included a healthy skepticism of societal pressures on individuals.</p>

<blockquote><p>Even a society whose ethical standard is relatively high, is dangerous to the ethics of its members. If those things which form precisely the defects of a social code of ethics develop strongly, and if society exercises, further, an excessively strong spiritual influence on individuals, then the ethic of ethical personality is ruined. This happens in present-day society, whose ethical conscience is becoming fatally stunted by a bilogico-sociological ethic and this, moreover, finally corrupted by nationalism.</p>

<p>The great mistake of ethical thought down to the present time is that it fails to admit the essential difference between the morality of ethical personality and that which is established from the standpoint of society, and always thinks that it ought, and is able, to cast them in one piece. The result is that the ethic of personality is sacrificed to the ethic of society&hellip; .</p>

<p>The morality of ethical personality, then, and the morality which is established from the standpoint of society cannot be traced back the one to the other, and they are not of equal value&hellip;. Ethical progress consists in making up our minds to think pessimistically of the ethics of society. (pp. 294)</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 4, Hindrances on Society]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/08/18/philosophy-of-civilization-pt4.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-18T22:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/08/18/philosophy-of-civilization-pt4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long awaited continuation here as I was out of town for a while. I wanted to continue where I left off with Schweitzer&rsquo;s philosophy of civilization.</p>

<p>One of my favorite things about the book is how connected he shows philosophy to be with society, which was a major part of what he was trying to do. And it really is amazing to see how much of society and revolutions and all sorts of things (not to mention the words we use and the ways we think about thinks on a daily basis) were very much shaped by and perhaps out of philosophy. Not that they came directly from it, but how philosophy often shapes the way we look at the world, our sort of frame of reference—whether we like it and want to admit it or not.</p>

<p>As a quote I recently heard from John Keynes goes:</p>

<blockquote><p>The ideas of economists and political philosophers, both when they are right and when they are wrong, are more powerful than is commonly understood. Indeed the world is ruled by little else. Practical men, who believe themselves to be quite exempt from any intellectual influence, are usually the slaves of some defunct economist. Madmen in authority, who hear voices in the air, are distilling their frenzy from some academic scribbler of a few years back. I am sure that the power of vested interests is vastly exaggerated compared with the gradual encroachment of ideas.</p>

<p>John Maynard Keynes // The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money</p></blockquote>

<p>Yikes. Okay.. so the previous post I attempted to give a sort of overview of some of the movements in philosophy and ethics Schweitzer talks about. Here I want to share a few snippets from the book on how he characterizes society at the time, or you could say the effects of the ideas of the time. He was in and saw his time as at a cusp, as it literally was, of some horrific things, and so he&rsquo;s speaking to a different time. But I don&rsquo;t think you have to reach very far to see some of these same mentalities and even effects going on today. We prize so many of these characteristics which, though they do bring us so many amazing technologies, perhaps they also bring something else.</p>

<blockquote><p>[T]hrough our methods of work we have suffered loss spiritually and as individuals just in proportion as the material output of our collective activity has increased. Here, too, is an illustration of that tragic law which says that every gain brings with it, somehow or other, a corresponding loss. (p. 14)</p></blockquote>

<h3>Individuals Overworked</h3>

<blockquote><p>To the want of freedom we have to add the evil of overstrain. For two or three generations numbers of individuals have been living as workers merely, not as human beings. Whatever can be said in a general way about the moral and spiritual significance of labour has no bearing on what they have to do. An excessive amount of labour is the rule today in every circle of society, with the result that the labourer&rsquo;s spiritual element cannot possibly thrive. This overwork his him indirectly even in his childhood, for his parents, caught in the inexorable toils of work, cannot devote themselves to his up-bringing as they should. Thus his development is robbed of something which can never be made good, and later in life, when he himself is the slave of over-long hours, he feels more and more the need of external distractions. To spend the time left to him for leisure in self-cultivation, or in serious intercourse with his fellows or with books, requires a mental collectedness and self-control which he finds every difficult. Complete idleness, forgetfulness, and diversion from his usual activities are a physical necessity. He does not want to think, and seeks not self-improvement, but entertainment, that kind of entertainment, moreover, which makes least demand upon his spiritual faculties.</p>

<p>The mentality of this mass of individuals, spiritually relaxed and incapable of self-collectedness, reacts upon all those institutions which ought to serve the cause of culture, and therewith of civilization. The theatre takes a second place behind the pleasure resort or the picture show, and the instructive book behind the diverting one. An ever increasing proportion of periodicals and newspapers have to accommodate themselves to the necessity of putting their matter before their readers in the shape which lets it be assimilated most easily. A comparison of the average newspapers of today with those of fifty or sixty years ago shows how thoroughly such publications have had to change their methods in this respect.</p>

<p>When once the spirit of superficiality has penetrated into the institutions which ought to sustain the spiritual life, these exercise on their part a reflex influence on the society which they have brought to this conditions, and force on all alike this state of mentality vacuity.</p>

<p>How completely this want of thinking power has become a second nature in men today is shown by the kind of sociability which it produces. When two of them meet for a conversation each is careful not to see that their talk does not go beyond generalities or develop into a real exchange of ideas. No one has anything of his own to give out, and everyone is haunted by a sort of terror lest anything original should be demanded from him.</p>

<p>The spirit produced in such a society of never-concentrated minds is rising among us as an ever growing force, and it results in a lowered conception of what man should be. In ourselves, as in others, we look for nothing but vigour in productive work, and resign ourselves to the abandonment of any higher ideal. (p. 11)</p></blockquote>

<h3>Over Specialization</h3>

<blockquote><p>The artisan of to-day does not understand his trade as a whole in the way in which his predecessor did. He no longer learns like the latter, to work the wood or the metal through all the stages of manufacture&hellip; Consequently his reflectiveness, his imagination, and his skill are no longer called out by ever varying difficulties in the work, and his creative and artistic powers are atrophied. In place of the normal self-consciousness which is promoted by work into the doing of which he must put his whole power of thought and his whole personality, there comes a self-satisfaction which is content with a fragmentary ability which, it may be admitted, is perfect, and this self-satisfaction is persuaded by its perfection in mastering details to overlook its imperfection in dealing with the whole.</p>

<p>Because in the complicated business world of today only undertakings with abundant capital behind them can maintain their existence, the place of the small, independent dealer is being taken more and more completely by the employee&hellip; .
The lack of freedom which results is made worse still because the factory system creates continually growing agglomerations of people who are thereby compulsorily separated from the soil which feeds them, from their own homes and from nature. Hence comes serious psychical injury. There is only too much truth in the paradoxical saying that abnormal life begins with the loss of one&rsquo;s own field and dwelling place. (p. 10)</p></blockquote>

<h3>Over-organization</h3>

<blockquote><p>The most widespread danger which material achievements bring with them for civilization consists in the fact that through the revolutions in the conditions of life men become in greater numbers unfree, instead of free. The type of man who once cultivated his own bit of land becomes a worker who tends a machine in a factory; manual workers and independent tradespeople become employees. They lose the elementary freedom of the man who lives in his own house and finds himself in immediate connection with Mother Earth. Further, they no longer have the extensive and unbroken consciousness of responsibility of those who live by their own independent labour. The conditions of their existence are therefore unnatural&hellip;.</p>

<p>To a certain extent we have all of us, under modern conditions, become unfree men. In every rank of life we have from decade to decade, if not from year to year, to carry on a harder struggle for existence. Overwork, physical or mental or both, is our lot. We can no longer find time to collect and order our thoughts. Our spiritual dependence increases at the same rate as our material dependence. In every direction we are the victims of conditions of dependence which in former times were never known in such universality and such strength. Economic, social, and political organizations, which are steadily becoming more and more complete, are getting us more and more into their power. The State with its increasingly rigid organization holds us under a control which is growing more and more decisive and inclusive. In every respect, therefore, our individual existence is depreciated. It is becoming ever more difficult to be a personality. (pp. 87-88)</p></blockquote>

<p>I picked out here just a few, of the many, points he makes about what was happening in society. All of which were connected with his point that philosophy was changing and shaping the way people thought and lived. People seemed to be becoming less people and more instruments, whose duty was to build up society, or to produce something. And in his account, no one was really talking about how philosophy was doing this, much less what philosophy, or western philosophy, was even aiming for, or what civilization is and should be. He describes philosophy as having become empty, mechanistic, losing spirit and conviction, being infatuated in its achievements, and in facts, and less with fundamental questions. Questions of humanity and meaning were left only to some obscure corner, and the spirit and creativity that once was in philosophy and in education was missing. And this was bleeding over into all sorts of areas, and influencing how people lived and treated one another on a grand scale.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Descartes - Meditations]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/05/26/descartes-meditations.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T23:02:44Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/05/26/descartes-meditations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/descartes.jpg" class="alignright" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy not to see a person like Descartes' significance for his time, not being in it and submersed in the changes and questions of the time. Him, along with people like Copernicus, Newton, Pascal and Galileo, launched the world out of the medieval period. And this book is one of the major landmarks in that movement&mdash;a movement who&rsquo;s authority became less grounded in the Bible and other ancient texts and more based in the mind and in reason. It was people like him who brought the world to all its crazy technological advances. A skeptical yet persistent mind that sought after certainty and perfection, and believed it could always be achieved. He not only kicked off modern philosophy with these thoughts, but he partook in some major achievements. Much of his mathematics, like the x y coordinate system, is the basis of much of what we use today.  He&rsquo;s apparently a pretty big deal (despite him often being only an entertaining topic of conversation in philosophy 101).</p>

<p><strong>Misc thoughts while reading Meditations</strong></p>

<p>Compared to Discourse on Method, Meditations goes more in depth into his thought process and his conclusions, something that was lacking in Discourse, which makes it a bit more interesting to read. The book plays as if it were a journal of daily meditations, though it unfortunately most likely did not happen this way.</p>

<p>I have yet to get too deep down the whole truth debate. I was hoping that midway through I would feel a bit psychedelic, but that didn&rsquo;t happen. Some of it, as Descartes does and admits, seems a bit goofy. But perhaps it&rsquo;s necessary, and despite this book being an attempt to pin down certainty, I think it also shows how uncertain we often are when we dig deeper and how feeble our knowledge is. Practically how far down this can you go, and how far would you really ever want to go?</p>

<p>Descartes seems very reasonable in some areas, and not so much in others. One example is his assumption-turned-fact of an infinite perfect God existing. His ideas and attributes of perfection are very anthropomorphic and I think at some level kind of arbitrary. It seems he was digging for something to grasp on to and God was it. The thing that was already implanted in his mind that gave him a grounding he needed and wanted.</p>

<p>It makes sense, give when he was around, his obsession for certainty and the desire to have his mind work like mathematics, but it seems very maddening and anxious. I think that&rsquo;s where people like Kierkegaard come in against some of these mindsets. And not only does it seem maddening and anxious, it seems perhaps the beginning of a mindset of rationalized and dismissive injustices. People ranked on a scale of imperfect to perfect, better and worse, more useful and less useful. The utility of the mind being prized, and the productive prized above the unproductive. A faulty way of life or thought process is simply a imperfection of your very mechanistic humanity.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<h3>Part One</h3>

<p><em>About the Things We May Doubt</em></p>

<p>Things formerly perceived as true he now sees as false. Instead of re-assessing every thought he had, he decides to rip away his entire foundation and build on top of another.</p>

<p>The senses sometimes deceive us. And even though there are many things that seem matter of fact, like having a body and hands and feet, it may be just an imagining, like a crazy person thinking he was something he was not. And beyond this, life could all be a dream. There are times dreams seem so real that in the moment you can&rsquo;t distinguish. However, there do appear more simple things like mathematics that seem to be universal and undeniable whether while dreaming or awake. God seems one of those things, but let us even doubt his existence, or let us suppose that he does exists and is deceiving us at every moment.</p>

<h3>Part Two</h3>

<p><em>Of the Nature of the Human Mind; and that it is Easier to Know than the Body</em></p>

<p>With all this doubting, perhaps there is nothing that I can find to be certain in the world. In considering that there is no physical world or that I have no senses I can perceive myself still in my mind without a body. And even if there were a giant deceiver, as long as I am thinking, I am. I exist.</p>

<p>He continues to cling to this notion and begins seeing a greater and greater separation between his mind and his body. Though he perceives the physical through the senses, it is only in his mind that he has the intuition and understanding to perceive and judge, which are still themselves feeble. He concludes he can see himself nothing more as a mind, and the only thing he still cannot doubt is that he exists.</p>

<h3>Part Three</h3>

<p><em>Of God that he exists</em></p>

<p>Here, Descartes says he closes his eyes. He attempts to get more familiar with himself. He is assured that he is a being which thinks. He has made a general rule that only the things that are <em>clear</em> and <em>distinct</em> to him can be accepted as true. He was certain again that though he perceived objects outside of him and could not be certain of their nature, he could be certain only of the idea that he had about them.</p>

<p>Descartes reflects more on the way the mind perceives. It takes in these externals, it judges, it feels, it imagines. And this ability of understanding seems engrained in his nature, as if implanted inside of him. It does not seem to come from the will. There must be some faculty or power that is helping.</p>

<p>And just like the mind seems to take in these things from the outside, so there seems with everything to be a cause. And this cause must be more perfect than the effect. It cannot infinitely regress. There must be a starting point, a first idea. Here Descartes concludes he is not alone. There must be something else besides him, other beings, or another being.</p>

<p>Here he goes on to prove the existence of God. There must be something else. There must be a cause. And there must be something perfect and infinite, how else would he have this idea of God, and why else would he constantly be searching for more perfection?</p>

<h3>Part Four</h3>

<p><em>Of Truth and Error</em></p>

<p>Having begun to detach himself more and more from the physical, Descartes attempts here to go further into the immaterial, of the mind and of God, both of which he at this points believes he can understand much more than anything physical.</p>

<blockquote><p>And when I consider that I doubt, that is to say, that I am an incomplete and dependent being, the idea a complete and independent being, that is to say of God presents itself to my mind with such distinctness and clearness, and, from the fact alone that this idea is found in me, or that I, who possess this idea, am or exist, I conclude so evidently that God exists, and that my existence depends entirely on him in each moment of my life, that I do not think that the human mind can know anything with more clearness and certainty.</p></blockquote>

<p>He reflects that God, being perfect, would never deceive, since deceit is imperfection. The deceit I have must not come from God, but it must be from myself, it must be my error, my imperfection, my defect. I am a midway point between this perfect and infinite God and nothingness, and my imperfection and error is simply a misuse of my will. To escape error and come to truth, I must only fix my attention sufficiently on the perfect and weed out only the clear and distinct.</p>

<h3>Part Five</h3>

<p><em>Of the Essense of Material Things; and, Once More of God, that He Exists</em></p>

<p>Descartes now wants to emerge himself out of all this doubt and see if anything can now be known about the material. He perceives that there is length, width, height, duration in the physical. These are seen clearly and distinctly. He reflects on Geomotry, and that there are these truths which you can still imagine apart from the physical world. He finds that God&rsquo;s existence is no less real to him than a number, than to mathematics.</p>

<p>He thinks about the association between certain things. A mountain must always have a valley. God certainly must involve existence. I can&rsquo;t conceive of anything which absolutely necessitates existence but God. He must exist. And his existence can give certainty to everything else. There is a possibility of acquiring perfect knowledge.</p>

<blockquote><p>But after I have discovered that God exists, recognizing at the same time that all things depend on him, and that he is no deceiver, and consequently judged that everything I perceive clearly and distinctly cannot fail to be true, although I no longer have present in my mind the reasons for my judgement, no contrary reason can be adduced which could ever make me doubt its truth, provided that I remember that I once clearly and distinctly comprehended it&hellip;.</p>

<p>But even if I were asleep, everything which is presented to my mind clearly, is absolutely true. And thus I recognize very clearly that the certainty and truth of all knowledge depends on the sole knowledge of the true God, so that, before I knew him, I could not know any other thing perfectly. And now that I know him, I have the means of acquiring a perfect knowledge of an infinity of things, not only relative to him, but also concerning physical nature, in so far as it serves as the object of the proofs of mathematicians, who are not concerned with its actual existence.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Part Six</h3>

<p><em>Of the Existence of Material Things, and of the Real Distinction between the Soul and the Body of Man</em></p>

<p>Descartes inquires more about the material here. He sees a difference between imagining something and conceiving things. He can imagine certain things, like a triangle, that he can hold intellectually and prove.  There are other things which he cannot imagine but can only perceive them, or experience them, such as a polygon with a thousand sides. And I cannot prove the existence of my body in my mind, it&rsquo;s only through perception that I can experience it, only through something external coming to my mind through the senses, something which is actually more vivid than the mind. Descartes finds that there is a high probability that these externals exist because of this.</p>

<p>He continues thinking, and remembers again that the senses can deceive. He cannot know them fully but he can know himself, that he is a being that exists and thinks. He finds that this is essentially what he is, and that he could exist just fine without his body. The mind, then, is necessarily separate from the body.</p>

<p>After continuing in his scepticism and in his reflections on the mind and the body and these senses, he remembers, and concludes that since God exists, and since he is no deceiver, there must be some truth to this physical world. He must contain the ability to correct the falsity in his views. There must be a means within himself for certainty, and Nature can indeed teach him at least some truth.</p>

<p>With this Descartes is satisfied. He wakes from his slumber and admits that it was all a bit silly. He needs not doubt anymore, and reviews that man is indeed very prone to error, and we should recognize this weakness in our nature.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Descartes - Discourse on Method]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/04/20/descartes-discourse-on-method.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-20T13:51:22Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/04/20/descartes-discourse-on-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/descartes.jpg" class="alignright" />
I decided it was time to get to Descartes. A must read before I continue further. I was not super excited to read Descartes, but I did find it more entertaining than expected, seeing a lot of connections to things a lot of us have heard. This is his Discourse on Method, and I&rsquo;ll be reading Meditations next.</p>

<h2>Thoughts</h2>

<p>I enjoyed the sort of letter style Descartes wrote this in. It was like a letter he wrote to a friend, a brief account of his journey through his experiment and his conclusions.</p>

<p>I was expecting it to be quite dull, but I did find his thought process entertaining to read and picture in his place in history. He has an obsessive need for certainty and logic and rationality. If only I can think hard enough (maybe I&rsquo;ll even lock myself in a room!) I will figure it out! It&rsquo;s like a fusion of curiosity, mixed with the assumption that thought can operate just like mathematics, along with the hope (or maybe need) to uphold and prove the idea that God exists and is good and perfect and logical (just like math!). It painted a sort of boring (and I&rsquo;d venture to say, perhaps even dangerous) picture of God. His logic in some of these places seemed also to be a bit goofy (e.g. I can think of the idea of &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; therefore there must be something perfect that created me, therefore God exists.. and is perfect!&mdash;phew!).</p>

<p>It seemed to be a precursor to a lot of goofy apologetical arguments still used today (Though Anselm who was before him enjoyed a similar style of argument to prove God&rsquo;s perfect justice and link it with atonement). One point he makes is that one of the greatest things that leads man astray is the thought that God does not exist and that man is just another animal. This seems to be a driving force to prove God&rsquo;s existence, the distinction between the mind/soul/rational/eternal-nature of man and his body, and man&rsquo;s far superior nature to those stupid, silly, and soulless animals.</p>

<p>If I were 7 years younger, and lived 500 years ago maybe this would have blown my mind. His question and approach is a creative one, which I do enjoy. The idea of starting everything, and all of thought, from scratch is an interesting, and fun, and maybe even an important one. But (at least in the current moment) it is hard to get myself to a place where his questions have relevance. And he seems overly concerned with making certain his proofs that he leaps a bit too far ahead of himself to give certainty to all those skeptics out there.</p>

<h2>Brief summary of Discourse on Method</h2>

<p><strong>Part One:</strong> Descartes looves math (&ldquo;because of it&rsquo;s certainty and self-evidence&rdquo;). Theology teaches you how to get into Heaven, philosophy teaches you how to win admiration of the &ldquo;less learned.&rdquo; Philosophy, he says, is always subject to disagreement and is always uncertain. Science, he says, is even subject to shifting foundations. He wanted to distinguish between true and false, and eventually learned not to accept or believe too firmly in anything in order to free himself from errors. He says he resolved to use the powers of his mind to choose his own paths of understanding.</p>

<p><strong>Part Two:</strong> Works composed from several people are often less perfect than those from one. Architecture by one architect is is usually better than one with several architects. Has anyone considered rebuilding the foundation of of a house or town in order to rebuild it more beautifully? This is what Descartes is trying to do with his thought: throw away everything and rebuild thought that is entirely his own. Before, though, he decides to plan <strong>a method</strong> to get to true knowledge, something with only a <strong>few simple principles</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Accept nothing as true unless it was presented so clearly and so distinctly that I have no doubt about it.</li>
<li>Divide each difficulty that I am examining into as many parts as possible in order to help solve it.</li>
<li>Think orderly, and begin with the simplest and easiest things first, then gradually get to the more complex.</li>
<li>Be so thorough and complete so as to omit nothing.</li>
</ol>


<p>His thought is that, like his understanding of math, there cannot be anything so distant or hidden that one could not eventually discover it.</p>

<p><strong>Part Three:</strong> Descartes decides here to come up with <strong>a few maxims</strong> / moral codes to help him get by while he tears down and rebuilds his thought-castle.</p>

<ol>
<li>Obey the laws and customs of my country and live according to the most moderate opinions and actions of the people.</li>
<li>Be as firm and resolute in my actions as possible.</li>
<li>Attempt to conquer myself rather than fortune and accustom myself to believe that nothing is entirely in my power except my thoughts, that this will lead me to more contentedness, happiness and freedom.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Part four:</strong> This is where Descartes gets into his conclusions, of which he prefaces by saying he&rsquo;s not sure if he should say them since they are so abstract and unusual. He decides to reject everything he previously believed as proofs and to pretend that everything that had ever entered his mind was just a dream. It is here he discovers and concludes the thought: <em>I think therefore I am.</em> He goes on to say since he can imagine that his body does not exist, while still thinking, that the mind must be completely distinct from the body and that the essence of existence is in thinking, not in the material. This gives him some sort of ground for certainty, but he still has doubts. Here he quickly assumes that since he is not perfect, but he can think of something that is perfect, there must be a greater perfection more perfect than him, outside of himself. And since this thought was inside of him, it must have come from somewhere. Something less perfect must have been made by something more perfect, and the idea of perfect must have been given to him. Thus he has just proven the existence of God, and all the things that he saw as imperfect (doubt, inconstancy, sadness etc.) must not exist in this God. This he uses as a basis to say he does have some sturdy ground to rely on, and that if there is some confusion or anything in him, it is only because he is not perfect. Finally, he says that if we are ever confused, we should rely only on our reason, not our senses or imagination.</p>

<blockquote><p>For reason does not dictate that what we see or imagine thus is true, but it does tell us that all our ideas and notions must have some basis in truth, for it would not be possible that God, who is all perfect and true, should have put them in us unless it were so.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Part five:</strong> Here he starts to link the idea of a perfect God with laws of nature. He imagines that if God were to create another world it must operate in the same exact way as ours. He then has a handful of pages that talk about anatomy and blood flow and concludes that the body is like a machine, far better than anything a man has ever created, and thus, something more admirable must have created us. He talks, then, about the distinction between man and animal, how man is far superior to animal, that man has a rational mind and a reasonable soul that animal does not have. He concludes by saying this about the soul:</p>

<blockquote><p>it is of the greatest importance: for, after the error of those who deny the existence of God, which error I think I have sufficiently refuted above, there is nothing which leads feeble minds more readily astray from the straight path of virtue than to imagine that the soul of animals is of the same nature as our own, and that, consequently, we have nothing to fear or to hope for after this life, any more than have flies or ants; instead, when one knows how much they differ, one can understand much better the reasons which prove that our soul is of a nature entirely independent of the body, and that, consequently, it is not subject to die with it; then, since one cannot see other causes for its destruction, one is naturally led to judge from this that it is immortal.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Part six:</strong> Descartes concludes by proposing we move away from speculative philosophy to something more practical. That we can be certain of things and that only with experiment and reason can we make advancements. That we have not even begun to see the kinds of advancements in areas like medicine that could be made. There are simple principles and truths of nature that we can discover and wield and make public for the progress of each man. If anyone has any question or objection, send it to his publisher and he will be interested in replying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 3, An Historical Tour and the Problem of Western Philosophy]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/28/philosophy-of-civilization-pt3.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T08:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/28/philosophy-of-civilization-pt3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a large majority of The Philosophy Of Civilization, Schweitzer gives a bit of a tour of philosophy and history, overviewing some of the major people and periods. He starts with the problem of Western Philosophy, overviews history from the Greeks to the present, their struggle for a world-view, and then gives his new proposal. I won&rsquo;t go over all of his reflections, but I want to give a brief overview to at least setup some basics.</p>

<h2>Western Philosophy&rsquo;s Strength and Weakness</h2>

<p>The strength of Western Philosophy is in it&rsquo;s &ldquo;life-affirmation&rdquo; and it&rsquo;s &ldquo;optimistic-ethical&rdquo; thought. These are two terms Schweitzer uses, amongst many others, throughout the book. Western thought strived to be optimistic, and this, when held onto firmly, is what led society so far—to so much discover, deep thought, and invention.</p>

<blockquote><p>For us Westerners civilization consists in this: that we work simultaneously for the perfecting of ourselves and of the world&hellip; . The history of Western philosophy is the history of the struggle for an optimistic outlook on life. If in antiquity and in modern times the peoples of Europe have managed to produce a civilization, it is because the optimistic world-view was dominant in their thought, and held the pessimistic permanently in subjection, although it was not able to suppress it altogether. (pp. 94-95)</p></blockquote>

<p>Though it&rsquo;s strength of optimism brought it so far, its weakness is that it lacked a sufficient, basic, and thorough world-view to sustain itself. It was searching in the wrong places and attempting to give itself a foundation on unstable ideas. And when it&rsquo;s optimism led it to great achievement, it forgot to reflect upon itself and was wrecked in the results.</p>

<!-- Society became enamored with it's material achievement, with its progress. It rode its optimistic wave and became deceived by its results, infatuated with itself, and lost in it. It's holding to the natural sciences shook its optimism from itself. ..infatuation with the material came to pessimism which it wasn't able to see in itself or reconcile. It neglected to consider the pessimistic thought and resignation of the east—one which ultimately needs to be brought into view to come to a successful world-view (??). Philosophy had essentially lost it's duty—it lost it's reflection and creativity and ability to give meaning to the world. It became mechanical, academic, and an infatuation with it's own past. And throughout history, philosophy never succeeded in building a solid world-view or a single kernel of thought that would carry it through without destroying itself as it had begun to do. -->


<p></p>

<h2>Beginning with the Greeks</h2>

<p>Schweitzer starts with the Greeks who, he says, begin to free themselves from their underlying religion and belief in the gods and move to a world-view based on knowledge and thought.</p>

<p><strong>The sophist</strong> begin criticizing social life, deciding that morals are invented by society for its own interests. The thinking man is to free himself from this and make his own morals based on his pleasure and interests.</p>

<p><strong>Socrates</strong>, Schweitzer says goes only little further than them. <em>&ldquo;In the place of their simply pleasurable he put the rationally pleasurable.&rdquo;</em> His greatness lies in his attempt to ground ground himself in thought, reason, and inner conviction. His downfall is his obsession with the individual&rsquo;s relation to the state as well as, like the other Greeks, his attempt to link his thought with pleasure—that an individual&rsquo;s happiness can be connected to the interests of society.</p>

<blockquote><p>The conception of the rationally pleasurable, which was the legacy of Socrates, is not productive enough to keep a world alive. It is impossible to develop from it the ideas of a utilitarianism directed to the welfare of the community, although he believed he founded them in it. Ethical thought remains confided within the circle of the <em>ego</em>. Every attempt to ennoble the rationally pleasurable ends in life-affirmation changing into life-negation. On this logical fact was wrecked the ancient West, which, after the critical awakening  of the Greek spirit, could have been saved only by means of a reflective optimistic-ethical outlook on life. It was able to take seriously what Socrates gave it, but not to make it capable of producint life and civilization. Plato, too, and Aristotle, the two great independent thinkers of antiquity, are incapable of producing an ethic of action, and so giving civilization a firm foundation. (p. 121)</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>The Stoics</strong> attempt to widen Socrates' narrow vision into something more cosmic. They too though, are too caught up in questions of pleasure and non-pleasure and citizenship to really go beyond. And their difference in an attempt to find a world-view in what Schweitzer calls &ldquo;nature-philosophy&rdquo; only leads to resignation (I&rsquo;ll get back to this idea in a later post).</p>

<blockquote><p>Nature-philosophy only provides the cosmic background for the resignation to which ethics have come&hellip; . It is true that there is power in the preaching of resignation which ancient thought, no longer ignorant about life, allows to go forth to mankind. Resignation is the lofty porch through which one enters upon ethics. But Epicurus and the Stoics stay on in this porch. Resignation becomes for them an ethiacal world-view. Hence they are incapable of leading ancient society from its ingenuous life-and-world-affirmation to a philosophy based on thought. (p. 121)</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Plato</strong> attempts to ground the Good on something more absolute in his forms, which Schweitzer says is devoid of content, supra-ethical, and dualistic. His virtues are the only practical element in his philosophy but have nothing to do with his conception of Good in his supra-ethical and immaterial world.</p>

<blockquote><p>The true ethic, then, is world-negation. To this view Plato was committed the moment he allowed the ethical to find its home in the world of pure Being. Thoughts of ascetic inactivity find expression in him side by side with the Greek feeling for reality, and it is confusing that he does not recognize the conflict between them, but speaks now in one sense, now in the other. His ethic is a chaos, and he himself an expert in inconsistency. Plato&rsquo;s ethic of world-negation is not an original creation; he takes it over in the Indian setting in which it is offered to him by Orphism and Pythagoreanism. By what route there found its way into Greek thought this pessimism which had been thought out to a system and equipped with the doctrine of re-incarnation, we do not know, and shall probably never learn&hellip; . (p. 123)</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;ve heard different people comment on this dualism in Plato but when I had originally read him I didn&rsquo;t see it that way. I&rsquo;ll have to keep that in mind next time I read him&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Aristotle</strong>, Schweitzer says, attempts to make ethics more actionable, grounded in rational reflection and virtue acquired by practice. And though he finds something simple and practical, Schweitzer says it is valueless in itself as it attempts to come to conclusions without understanding itself.</p>

<blockquote><p>Aristotle is so firmly resolved not to have anything to do with the problem of the basic principle of ethics, that he will allow nothing to lead him to discuss it. He means to voyage along the coast, keep to facts, and deal with ethics as if they were a branch of natural science&hellip; .</p>

<p>It is because he misunderstands their nature that Aristotle cannot help ethics forward. Plato goes beyond Socrates and loses himself in abstractions. Aristotle, in order to maintain the connection with reality, aims lower than Socrates. He brings together material for a monumental building, and runs up a wooden shack. Among teachers of virtue he is one of the greatest. Nevertheless, the least of those who venture on the search for the basic principle of the ethical is greater than he. (p. 127)</p></blockquote>

<p>Schweitzer continues to reflect upon these and others, and he ends with the Greeks by concluding that they were unable to find something grounded to progress humanity. It was only with the later Greek thinkers that begin to find something more &ldquo;optimistic-ethical&rdquo; that would progress humanity, but they were too late.</p>

<blockquote><p>The optimistic-ethical monism of the later Stoics is like a sunbeam breaking through in the evening of the long, gloomy day of antiquity while the darkness of the middle ages is already drawing on, but it has no power to waken any civilization to life. The time for that is past. The spirit of antiquity, having failed to reach an ethical nature-philosophy, has become the prey of a pessimistic dualism in which no ethic of action is any longer possible; there can only be an ethic of purification.</p>

<p>The thoughts of Seneca, Epictetus, and Marcus Aurelius are the winter seeds of a coming civilization. (p. 140)</p></blockquote>

<h2>Rennaissance and Post-Rennaissance</h2>

<p>From the Greeks, Schweitzer moves to the Renaissance where he speaks of a new world-and-life-affirmation which breaks through as never before. This time begins to move towards nature and discovery, asking questions about governing laws and the universe and making them serviceable to itself. This new phase came quickly, Schweitzer says, but without much fruit. It had become optimistic, not because of a new deepened thought, but because its understanding of the world gave it power.</p>

<blockquote><p>[B]eginning at the end of the fourteenth century, and it arises as a protest against the medieval enslavement of the human spirit. The movement is helped to victory by the increasing knowledge of Greek Philosophy in its original form, which is the result of the migration to Italy about the middle of the fifteenth century of learned Greeks from Constantinople. Among the thinking men of that time there arises the believe that philosophy must be something more elemental and more living than Scholasticism taught.</p>

<p>But the thought of antiquity would not have been sufficient by itself to keep alive this new world-and-life-affirmation which appealed to it as a precedent. It had not, in truth, the mentality required. (p. 141)</p></blockquote>

<p>One interesting characteristic Schweitzer makes here is a transformation of pessimism to optimism, with the help of Christianity. Christianity&rsquo;s transformation, he says, is the decisive event of this the modern age.</p>

<blockquote><p>Under the steadily active influence of the new mentality, the world-view of Christianity changes, and becomes leavened with the yeast of the world-and-life-affirmation. It gradually begins to be accepted as self-evident that the spirit of Jesus does not renounce the world, but aims at transforming it. The early Christian concept of the Kingdom of God, which was born of pessimism and, thanks to Augustine, prevailed through the Middle Ages, is rendered impotent, and its place is taken by a conception which is the offspring of modern optimism&hellip; . During this period Christianity takes no account of what is happening to itself. It believes that it is remaining unaltered, whereas in reality, by this change from pessimism to optimism, it is surrendering its original character. (p. 143)</p></blockquote>

<p>Though post Reformation thought would view Jesus' teaching as an active action to transform the world, Schweitzer says it was not so—it is the paradox of his teaching that he had an active ethical teaching combined with an awaiting of the end of the world. The modern age overlooked this paradox and held to the optimism of his teaching, and combined it, he says, with the late stoicism of a rational and active ethic. Where they were once unable to come together because of these differing viewpoints, they now were able to because of a new bridge between their world-views.</p>

<p>The combination of this Stoic and Christian ethic with the achievements of discovery and invention brought a belief in progress which brought forth this new age. But as time went on, progress would begin to leave ethics behind until it brings ethics down with it. And this begins a great turning point having gone from pessimism to optimism, now it returns to pessimism again.</p>

<blockquote><p>But as the cart gets heavier and the road more difficult, so that ethics ought to lend their strength to help, they refuse, because they have no strength of their own. The cart begins to run backward, and carries belief in progress, and ethics with it, down the hill.</p>

<p>The task before philosophy was to change the world-and-life-affirmation which arose from enthusiasm over the attainments of discovery and invention into a deeper, inner world-and-life-affirmation arising out of thought about the universe and the life of man, and on that same foundation to build up an ethical system. But philosophy could do neither.</p>

<p>About the middle of the nineteenth century, when it has become perfectly clear that we are living with a world-and-life-affirmation which has its source merely in our confidence in discovery and invention and not in any profounder thought about the world and life, our fate is sealed. The modern optimistic-ethical world-view, after doing so much for the material development of civilization, has to collapse like a building erected already to a considerable height but on rotten foundations. (p. 149)</p></blockquote>

<h2>Ethics in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries</h2>

<p>These two centuries begin to go back to similar questions posed by the Greeks by asking how the self can be merged with altruism, or society as a whole. Many had attempted to put it under rational thought and argued that if an individual truly understands his own interests, he would connect them with the interests of society. Others had continued that thought and concluded that individuals left alone would only go towards their selfish desires, and authority had to compel them to do otherwise, by appealing to their egoism and material desires. Individuals could be could be regulated by society itself by using praise and blame. Hume had even apparently encouraged the love of fame, as it would keep one in the spotlight of others and encourage one to please them.</p>

<p>And against the more utilitarian viewpoints, others had proposed that morality is really the striving for perfection given to us by nature. There seemed to be a swirl of rational thought attempting to grasp something to build a society for the benefit of all its members, but Schweitzer points out as he does with the Greeks, that these thoughts end in resignation.</p>

<blockquote><p>The consideration, therefore, that egoism, rightly understood, will oblige the individual to resolve on activity which is directed to promoting the common good, is a ship which sails well, but leaks. (p. 152)</p>

<p>Ethical thought falls from one paradox into another. If, as in antiquity, it thinks out a system in which the activity that must be directed to the common good is not sufficiently represented, it arrives at ethics which are no longer ethics, and ends in resignation. If it assumes and starts from such an activity directed to the common good, it arrives at an ethic in which there is no ethical personality. Strange to say, it is unable to mark out the middle course and let an activity which is directed to the promotion of the common good spring from the ethical personality itself. (p. 158)</p></blockquote>

<p>Schweitzer begins here to point more towards his proposal that the ethical cannot be supported by rational thought alone, and especially not by attempting to merge spiritual happiness with material happiness. Maybe it could stand alone by an inner compulsion. Of this age he ends with a guy named Anthony Ashley-Cooper (aka Earl Shaftesbury) who became a major influence to the next generations, returning them back to the creative spirit of the Renaissance. About him Schweitzer says,</p>

<blockquote><p>he places its origin in feeling&hellip; . [T]he important thing is that he puts forward a living philosophy of nature in combination with ethics. He is convinced that harmony reigns in the universe and that man is meant to experience this harmony in himself. Aesthetic feeling and ethical thinking are for him forms of union with that divine life which struggles to find expression in the spiritual being of man as it does with nature. With Shaftesbury ethics descends from a rocky mountain range into a luxuriant plain. The utilitarians as yet know nothing of a world. Their ethic is restricted to considerations about the relation of the individual to society. The anti-utilitarians have some idea of a world, but not a correct one. They elaborate ethics with a formal theology and a formal philosophizing about the All, but Shaftesbury plants ethical thought in the universe of reality, which he himself contemplates through an idealising optimism, reaching thereby a direct and universal notion of the moral.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Rationalism and beyond</h2>

<p>With a rational and optimistic grounding and a strong belief in progress, society began to make great advancements, not only materially but through the beginning of tolerance, the end of witch trials and superstitious thought, torture becoming less and less used, and new ideals of all becoming educated. &ldquo;The war against ignorance is begun,&rdquo; Schweitzer says. A wave of enthusiasm from the previous generations was rode, but not for too long before people began to become critical of it, and Napoleon wreaked havoc on Europe, putting it &ldquo;in a condition of misery.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>The ethical and the optimistic come into power, therefore, in the philosophy of the eighteenth century, although they have not yet received any real foundation. Scepticism and materialism range around the fortress like hordes of unconquered enemies, thought at first without being dangerous; as a rule they have themselves absorbed no small amount of belief-in-progress and of ethical enthusiasm.  (pp. 167-168)</p></blockquote>

<p>Moving into the nineteenth century, society kept progressing, but it began to leave ethics behind. The sciences, biology and Darwinian thought began to mark their influence as society moved from the rational to the actual. Philosophy became mere academic review and it&rsquo;s creativity began to vanish. Questions of individual ethics became no longer interesting, progress no longer appreciated, and the conviction of the previous generations began to fade. And with this, the optimism western society once held became dull, the excitement of discovery gone, and only cold hard facts remained and the utility of every person sought after.</p>

<blockquote><p>When, at the close of the eighteenth century and the beginning of the nineteenth, the reaction against rationalism set in and criticism began to play upon it, its optimism was reproached as superficial and its ethics as sentimental. But the spiritual movements which criticize it and take its place cannot develop on the same lines what it accomplished, in spite of its manifold imperfections, by inspiring men with ideals of civilization grounded in reason. The energy of thought about civilization dwindles imperceptibly but steadily. In proportion as the world-view of rationalism is left behind, the feeling for actuality makes its influence felt, until at last, from the middle of the nineteenth century onwards, ideals are borrowed no longer from reason but from actuality, and we therewith sink still further into a state of uncivilization and lack of humanity. This is the clearest and most important of all the facts which can be established in the history of our civilization. (p. 91)</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 2, Crisis]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/06/philosophy-of-civilization-pt2.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T18:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/06/philosophy-of-civilization-pt2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Albert Schweitzer" title="Albert Schweitzer's Philosophy of Civilization (1924)" src="/assets/images/albert_schweitzer_philosophy_of_civilization.jpg" class="alignleft" /></p>

<blockquote><p>We are living today under the sign of the collapse of civilization. The situation has not been produced by the war; the latter is only a manifestation of it. The spiritual atmosphere has solidified into actual facts, which again react on it with disastrous results in every respect&hellip; . It is clear now to everyone that the suicide of civilization is in progress. What yet remains of it is no longer safe. It is still standing, indeed, because it was not exposed to the destructive pressure which overwhelmed the rest, but, like the rest, it is built upon rubble, and the next landslide will very likely carry it away.</p></blockquote>

<p>Wow&hellip; It is fascinating to look back and learn about how society viewed itself and the world. It was 1923 when he published this book, between both world wars, which gives you an idea where he&rsquo;s coming from. There seemed to be an obsession in the air for progress, for achievement. Imperialism, the white man&rsquo;s burden, over industrialization, survival of the fittest, social utilitarianism, social Darwinism, human zoos. The ideals and ideas seemed to trump the value of life. Schweitzer is attempting to grapple with and reflect on the state of society. What led it here? What can we learn from history? What does true civilization look like? Is there a way out?</p>

<blockquote><p>We want to get into our hands the key of the secret, so that we may with it unlock the new age, the age in which the worn out becomes again unworn and the spiritual and ethical can no longer get worn out. We must study the history of civilization otherwise than as our predecessors did, or we shall be finally lost.</p></blockquote>

<p>Ultimately he finds that society is and must be ethical, that it lacks a world view, and must find one that is simple, optimistic, and upholds the value of all life.</p>

<blockquote><p>Entering on the question as to what is the real essential nature of civilization, I come to the pronouncement that this is ultimately ethical. I know that in thus stating the problem as a moral one I shall surprise and even disgust the spirit of our times, which is accustomed to move amidst aesthetic, historical and material considerations. I imagine, however, that I am myself enough of an artist and also of an historian to be able to comprehend the aesthetic and historical elements in civilization, and that, as a modern physician and surgeon, I am sufficiently modern to appreciate the glamour of the technical and material attainments of our age&hellip; .</p>

<p>Only when we are able to attribute a real meaning to the world and to life shall we be able to also give ourselves to such actions as will produce results of real value. As long as we look on our existence in the world as meaningless, there is no point whatever in desiring to effect anything in the world&hellip; .</p></blockquote>

<p>In the next few posts I&rsquo;ll be going over a few of the main points I&rsquo;ve gathered throughout the book, his reflections on society and philosophy, and his solution.</p>

<blockquote><p>I do not know how how many, or how few, will allow themselves to be persuaded to travel with me on the road indicted above. What I desire above all things—and this is the crux of the whole affair—is that we should all recognize fully that our present entire lack of any theory of the universe is the ultimate source of all the catastrophes and misery of our times, and that we should work together for a theory of the universe and of life, in order that thus we may arrive at a mental disposition which shall make us really and truly civilized men.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 1, Albert Schweitzer]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt1.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T11:23:00Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Albert Schweitzer" title="Albert Schweitzer (1875-1965)" src="/assets/images/Albert_Schweitzer_1952.jpg" class="alignleft" />
I wanted to start off by reviewing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Schweitzer">Albert Schweitzer&rsquo;s</a> book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Philosophy-Civilization-Albert-Schweitzer/dp/0879754036">The Philosophy of Civilization</a>. I&rsquo;ve grown to really admire him as a person and this book is easily one of my all time favorite books. It&rsquo;s written so elegantly, so in depth, and still is so profound and simple. He gives one of the most engaging and practical overviews of history and philosophy that I have ever read. And his ethic—"reverence for life"—is one that I love, and connect with. The basic message of the book is something I think everyone should be exposed to.</p>

<p>Before getting into the book though, I first want to share a little about Schweitzer. Besides noting his lovely hair and mustache, for starters, he is one of the more remarkable people I&rsquo;ve read about. I had primarily known him for his work on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/quest-historical-Jesus-critical-progress-ebook/dp/B00CE1PB1Q/">Jesus</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mysticism-Apostle-Albert-Schweitzer-Library/dp/0801860989">Paul</a>. But he was also a teacher, a pastor, a music scholar—he wrote a 400 page book on Bach in his spare time in French (apparently while teaching <em>and</em> in school for his medical doctorate, and later completely rewrote it&hellip; making it 800 pages&hellip; in German&hellip; because simply translating it wouldn&rsquo;t have sufficed&hellip; he apparently wanted to re-saturate himself with the content to let it sit—authentically—in the German language). He studied medicine for about 6 years, and afterwards became a doctor in Africa, dedicating the rest of his life to serve humanity (I&rsquo;m not sure how he accomplished all he did in his lifetime and kept his sanity). In his autobiography he writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>The plan which I meant now to put into execution had been in my mind for a long time, having been conceived so long ago as my student days. It struck me as incomprehensible that I should be allowed to lead such a happy life, while I saw so many people around me wrestling with care and suffering. Even at school I had felt stirred whenever I got a glimpse of the miserable home surroundings of some of my schoolfellows and compared them with the absolutely ideal conditions in which we children of the parsonage at Günsbach lived. While at the university and enjoying the happiness of being able to study and even to produce some results in science and art, I could not help thinking continually of others who were denied that happiness by their material circumstances or their health. Then one brilliant summer morning at Günsbach, during the Whitesuntide holidays—it was in 1896—there came to me, as I awoke, the thought that I must not accept this happiness as a matter of course, but must give something in return for it. Proceeding to think the matter out at once with calm deliberation, while the birds were singing outside, I settled with myself before I got up, that I would consider myself justified in living till I was thirty for science and art, in order to devote myself from that time forward to the direct service of humanity. Many a time already had I tried to settle what meaning lay hidden for me in the saying of Jesus! &ldquo;Whosoever would save his life shall lose it, and whosoever shall lose his life for My sake and the Gospels shall save it.&rdquo; Now the answer was found. In addition to the outward, I now had inward happiness."</p>

<p>What would be the character of the activities thus planned for the future was not yet clear to me. I left it to circumstances to guide me. One thing only was certain, that it must be directly human service, however inconspicuous the sphere of it.</p></blockquote>

<p>I really got drawn to Schweitzer after reading a small book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Albert-Schweitzers-friendship-Erica-Anderson/dp/B00005VBZH/">Albert Schweitzer&rsquo;s Gift of Friendship</a>, by Erica Anderson. She had befriended him through wanting to film a documentary about him (which she was eventually able to do, after much reluctance by him—she found out after asking him that he once said to another who requested, &ldquo;I would rather burn in hell than have a film made of my life&rdquo;). The film won an academy award for best documentary in 1952. In her book, she writes about her entire experience with him, from the first letters she wrote him, to meeting him for the first time, and her times with him over the years. Her book and documentary give a very personal insight into his life, his humor, and his character and personality, one you wouldn&rsquo;t be able to get by reading his autobiography. He has a unique blend of compassion, intellect, purpose and humor. I could share a bunch of quotes and moments from her book, but for now I want to end with a quote from the documentary she filmed. Schweitzer shares a moment from his childhood:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was hard for me to keep my mind on my studies when my eyes were always wandering outside to the wonders of nature itself&hellip;.  At the age of 9, my life took a new turn. Every morning and evening, I walked nearly two miles over the hills to the school where my parents decided to send me. I was delighted to take these walks by myself&hellip; to think my own thoughts. How well I came to know the changing seasons. But the sheer youthful joy of being alive was something I never knew. I think this is true of many children who appear outwardly care free and content. As far back as I can remember, I was shocked by the suffering I observed in nature. Suffering brought about by the relentless struggle for existence. Still more shocking to me was the pain and mystery inflicted on dumb helpless animals, by the negligence and thoughtlessness of man. Even before I started to go to school, I couldn&rsquo;t understand why I was only expected to pray for human beings when I said my prayers at night. So when my mother had drawn the shudders, and blown out the candle, and kissed me goodnight I secretly said another prayer for all that had life. A prayer that I had made up myself. &ldquo;Dear God, protect and bless all living creatures. Keep them from evil. And let them sleep in peace.&rdquo;</p>

<p>An experience I had during these years made a lasting impression on me. A neighbor&rsquo;s son and I had made slingshots from rubber bands. One Sunday morning he said to me, &ldquo;Come on, let&rsquo;s go up the mountain and shoot birds. This seemed a horrible idea, but I didn&rsquo;t dare object for fear of being laughed at. The birds were singing sweetly in the morning sunshine, so unafraid of us. Crouching like an indian, my friend put a stone in his slingshot and took aim. Obeying his look of command, I did the same, with acute pains of conscience. At that moment the sounds of church bells began to mingle with the sunshine and the birds' song. To me, it was a voice from heaven. I frightened away the birds, to protect them from my friend&rsquo;s shot, and ran home. Ever since, when morning bells ring out in the sunshine, I gratefully remember those bells. For they rang into my heart the commandment, "thought shalt not kill.&rdquo; The matter in which this commandment speaks against killing and cruelty, worked upon me was the great experience of my childhood and youth. Gradually I came to the unshakeable conviction, that we may bring death and pain to a fellow creature only on the compulsion of absolute necessity, and that we must all feel the horror of causing suffering and death by thoughtlessness. I became more and more certain that all of us feel this way, but do not dare to affirm it. We are afraid of being ridiculed as sentimental. We allow ourselves to become callous.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<p>And, if you&rsquo;re interested in a few fun quotes from Erica&rsquo;s book:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/a6f3e4dc-6aa8-4eaa-b1ca-a4f59409aa1e?locale=en" target="_blank">On Erica&rsquo;s first visit</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/8e8d1818-79a4-4ab8-a7cb-a9ee86932d08?locale=en" target="_blank">I used to be lazy as a boy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/ed9c8b96-f585-48ce-b482-ff236d1a6ff2?locale=en" target="_blank">What&rsquo;s honor?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/6af4ffe4-41b8-49ec-92fc-da5552816a01?locale=en" target="_blank">They pick up man Schweitzer assumes needs a ride</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/8b14c990-cadc-4a91-a441-efe63f16d5a6?locale=en" target="_blank">On his routine</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baby Reincarnation]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/20/welcome.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T19:33:28Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/20/welcome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello world. A new born baby has arrived, delivered from that flying baby stork&hellip; not a human baby though&hellip; a website baby&hellip; it&rsquo;s the fifth reincarnation of this website. We&rsquo;ll see where this baby takes us. For now it will take it&rsquo;s form as an outlet for the interesting reads I find in front of my eyeballs. A place to gather my thoughts and attempt to understand them by writing about them and sharing. As a personal project, I&rsquo;m planning on reading a new book from a major philosopher each month for the next year, and then hopefully summarizing each as I go. So I&rsquo;ll start out by summarizing a few past reads and I&rsquo;ll go from there, probably sprinkling in some others along the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
