<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[]]></title>
  <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-26T23:02:50-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brent Wejrowski]]></name>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Descartes - Meditations]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/05/26/descartes-meditations.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T23:02:44Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/05/26/descartes-meditations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/descartes.jpg" class="alignright" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy not to see a person like Descartes' significance for his time, not being in it and submersed in the changes and questions of the time. Him, along with people like Copernicus, Newton, Pascal and Galileo, launched the world out of the medieval period. And this book is one of the major landmarks in that movement&mdash;a movement who&rsquo;s authority became less grounded in the Bible and other ancient texts and more based in the mind and in reason. It was people like him who brought the world to all its crazy technological advances. A skeptical yet persistent mind that sought after certainty and perfection, and believed it could always be achieved. He not only kicked off modern philosophy with these thoughts, but he partook in some major achievements. Much of his mathematics, like the x y coordinate system, is the basis of much of what we use today.  He&rsquo;s apparently a pretty big deal (despite him often being only an entertaining topic of conversation in philosophy 101).</p>

<p><strong>Misc thoughts while reading Meditations</strong></p>

<p>Compared to Discourse on Method, Meditations goes more in depth into his thought process and his conclusions, something that was lacking in Discourse, which makes it a bit more interesting to read. The book plays as if it were a journal of daily meditations, though it unfortunately most likely did not happen this way.</p>

<p>I have yet to get too deep down the whole truth debate. I was hoping that midway through I would feel a bit psychedelic, but that didn&rsquo;t happen. Some of it, as Descartes does and admits, seems a bit goofy. But perhaps it&rsquo;s necessary, and despite this book being an attempt to pin down certainty, I think it also shows how uncertain we often are when we dig deeper and how feeble our knowledge is. Practically how far down this can you go, and how far would you really ever want to go?</p>

<p>Descartes seems very reasonable in some areas, and not so much in others. One example is his assumption-turned-fact of an infinite perfect God existing. His ideas and attributes of perfection are very anthropomorphic and I think at some level kind of arbitrary. It seems he was digging for something to grasp on to and God was it. The thing that was already implanted in his mind that gave him a grounding he needed and wanted.</p>

<p>It makes sense, give when he was around, his obsession for certainty and the desire to have his mind work like mathematics, but it seems very maddening and anxious. I think that&rsquo;s where people like Kierkegaard come in against some of these mindsets. And not only does it seem maddening and anxious, it seems perhaps the beginning of a mindset of rationalized and dismissive injustices. People ranked on a scale of imperfect to perfect, better and worse, more useful and less useful. The utility of the mind being prized, and the productive prized above the unproductive. A faulty way of life or thought process is simply a imperfection of your very mechanistic humanity.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<h3>Part One</h3>

<p><em>About the Things We May Doubt</em></p>

<p>Things formerly perceived as true he now sees as false. Instead of re-assessing every thought he had, he decides to rip away his entire foundation and build on top of another.</p>

<p>The senses sometimes deceive us. And even though there are many things that seem matter of fact, like having a body and hands and feet, it may be just an imagining, like a crazy person thinking he was something he was not. And beyond this, life could all be a dream. There are times dreams seem so real that in the moment you can&rsquo;t distinguish. However, there do appear more simple things like mathematics that seem to be universal and undeniable whether while dreaming or awake. God seems one of those things, but let us even doubt his existence, or let us suppose that he does exists and is deceiving us at every moment.</p>

<h3>Part Two</h3>

<p><em>Of the Nature of the Human Mind; and that it is Easier to Know than the Body</em></p>

<p>With all this doubting, perhaps there is nothing that I can find to be certain in the world. In considering that there is no physical world or that I have no senses I can perceive myself still in my mind without a body. And even if there were a giant deceiver, as long as I am thinking, I am. I exist.</p>

<p>He continues to cling to this notion and begins seeing a greater and greater separation between his mind and his body. Though he perceives the physical through the senses, it is only in his mind that he has the intuition and understanding to perceive and judge, which are still themselves feeble. He concludes he can see himself nothing more as a mind, and the only thing he still cannot doubt is that he exists.</p>

<h3>Part Three</h3>

<p><em>Of God that he exists</em></p>

<p>Here, Descartes says he closes his eyes. He attempts to get more familiar with himself. He is assured that he is a being which thinks. He has made a general rule that only the things that are <em>clear</em> and <em>distinct</em> to him can be accepted as true. He was certain again that though he perceived objects outside of him and could not be certain of their nature, he could be certain only of the idea that he had about them.</p>

<p>Descartes reflects more on the way the mind perceives. It takes in these externals, it judges, it feels, it imagines. And this ability of understanding seems engrained in his nature, as if implanted inside of him. It does not seem to come from the will. There must be some faculty or power that is helping.</p>

<p>And just like the mind seems to take in these things from the outside, so there seems with everything to be a cause. And this cause must be more perfect than the effect. It cannot infinitely regress. There must be a starting point, a first idea. Here Descartes concludes he is not alone. There must be something else besides him, other beings, or another being.</p>

<p>Here he goes on to prove the existence of God. There must be something else. There must be a cause. And there must be something perfect and infinite, how else would he have this idea of God, and why else would he constantly be searching for more perfection?</p>

<h3>Part Four</h3>

<p><em>Of Truth and Error</em></p>

<p>Having begun to detach himself more and more from the physical, Descartes attempts here to go further into the immaterial, of the mind and of God, both of which he at this points believes he can understand much more than anything physical.</p>

<blockquote><p>And when I consider that I doubt, that is to say, that I am an incomplete and dependent being, the idea a complete and independent being, that is to say of God presents itself to my mind with such distinctness and clearness, and, from the fact alone that this idea is found in me, or that I, who possess this idea, am or exist, I conclude so evidently that God exists, and that my existence depends entirely on him in each moment of my life, that I do not think that the human mind can know anything with more clearness and certainty.</p></blockquote>

<p>He reflects that God, being perfect, would never deceive, since deceit is imperfection. The deceit I have must not come from God, but it must be from myself, it must be my error, my imperfection, my defect. I am a midway point between this perfect and infinite God and nothingness, and my imperfection and error is simply a misuse of my will. To escape error and come to truth, I must only fix my attention sufficiently on the perfect and weed out only the clear and distinct.</p>

<h3>Part Five</h3>

<p><em>Of the Essense of Material Things; and, Once More of God, that He Exists</em></p>

<p>Descartes now wants to emerge himself out of all this doubt and see if anything can now be known about the material. He perceives that there is length, width, height, duration in the physical. These are seen clearly and distinctly. He reflects on Geomotry, and that there are these truths which you can still imagine apart from the physical world. He finds that God&rsquo;s existence is no less real to him than a number, than to mathematics.</p>

<p>He thinks about the association between certain things. A mountain must always have a valley. God certainly must involve existence. I can&rsquo;t conceive of anything which absolutely necessitates existence but God. He must exist. And his existence can give certainty to everything else. There is a possibility of acquiring perfect knowledge.</p>

<blockquote><p>But after I have discovered that God exists, recognizing at the same time that all things depend on him, and that he is no deceiver, and consequently judged that everything I perceive clearly and distinctly cannot fail to be true, although I no longer have present in my mind the reasons for my judgement, no contrary reason can be adduced which could ever make me doubt its truth, provided that I remember that I once clearly and distinctly comprehended it&hellip;.</p>

<p>But even if I were asleep, everything which is presented to my mind clearly, is absolutely true. And thus I recognize very clearly that the certainty and truth of all knowledge depends on the sole knowledge of the true God, so that, before I knew him, I could not know any other thing perfectly. And now that I know him, I have the means of acquiring a perfect knowledge of an infinity of things, not only relative to him, but also concerning physical nature, in so far as it serves as the object of the proofs of mathematicians, who are not concerned with its actual existence.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Part Six</h3>

<p><em>Of the Existence of Material Things, and of the Real Distinction between the Soul and the Body of Man</em></p>

<p>Descartes inquires more about the material here. He sees a difference between imagining something and conceiving things. He can imagine certain things, like a triangle, that he can hold intellectually and prove.  There are other things which he cannot imagine but can only perceive them, or experience them, such as a polygon with a thousand sides. And I cannot prove the existence of my body in my mind, it&rsquo;s only through perception that I can experience it, only through something external coming to my mind through the senses, something which is actually more vivid than the mind. Descartes finds that there is a high probability that these externals exist because of this.</p>

<p>He continues thinking, and remembers again that the senses can deceive. He cannot know them fully but he can know himself, that he is a being that exists and thinks. He finds that this is essentially what he is, and that he could exist just fine without his body. The mind, then, is necessarily separate from the body.</p>

<p>After continuing in his scepticism and in his reflections on the mind and the body and these senses, he remembers, and concludes that since God exists, and since he is no deceiver, there must be some truth to this physical world. He must contain the ability to correct the falsity in his views. There must be a means within himself for certainty, and Nature can indeed teach him at least some truth.</p>

<p>With this Descartes is satisfied. He wakes from his slumber and admits that it was all a bit silly. He needs not doubt anymore, and reviews that man is indeed very prone to error, and we should recognize this weakness in our nature.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Descartes - Discourse on Method]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/04/20/descartes-discourse-on-method.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-20T13:51:22Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/04/20/descartes-discourse-on-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/descartes.jpg" class="alignright" />
I decided it was time to get to Descartes. A must read before I continue further. I was not super excited to read Descartes, but I did find it more entertaining than expected, seeing a lot of connections to things a lot of us have heard. This is his Discourse on Method, and I&rsquo;ll be reading Meditations next.</p>

<h2>Thoughts</h2>

<p>I enjoyed the sort of letter style Descartes wrote this in. It was like a letter he wrote to a friend, a brief account of his journey through his experiment and his conclusions.</p>

<p>I was expecting it to be quite dull, but I did find his thought process entertaining to read and picture in his place in history. He has an obsessive need for certainty and logic and rationality. If only I can think hard enough (maybe I&rsquo;ll even lock myself in a room!) I will figure it out! It&rsquo;s like a fusion of curiosity, mixed with the assumption that thought can operate just like mathematics, along with the hope (or maybe need) to uphold and prove the idea that God exists and is good and perfect and logical (just like math!). It painted a sort of boring (and I&rsquo;d venture to say, perhaps even dangerous) picture of God. His logic in some of these places seemed also to be a bit goofy (e.g. I can think of the idea of &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; therefore there must be something perfect that created me, therefore God exists.. and is perfect!&mdash;phew!).</p>

<p>It seemed to be a precursor to a lot of goofy apologetical arguments still used today (Though Anselm who was before him enjoyed a similar style of argument to prove God&rsquo;s perfect justice and link it with atonement). One point he makes is that one of the greatest things that leads man astray is the thought that God does not exist and that man is just another animal. This seems to be a driving force to prove God&rsquo;s existence, the distinction between the mind/soul/rational/eternal-nature of man and his body, and man&rsquo;s far superior nature to those stupid, silly, and soulless animals.</p>

<p>If I were 7 years younger, and lived 500 years ago maybe this would have blown my mind. His question and approach is a creative one, which I do enjoy. The idea of starting everything, and all of thought, from scratch is an interesting, and fun, and maybe even an important one. But (at least in the current moment) it is hard to get myself to a place where his questions have relevance. And he seems overly concerned with making certain his proofs that he leaps a bit too far ahead of himself to give certainty to all those skeptics out there.</p>

<h2>Brief summary of Discourse on Method</h2>

<p><strong>Part One:</strong> Descartes looves math (&ldquo;because of it&rsquo;s certainty and self-evidence&rdquo;). Theology teaches you how to get into Heaven, philosophy teaches you how to win admiration of the &ldquo;less learned.&rdquo; Philosophy, he says, is always subject to disagreement and is always uncertain. Science, he says, is even subject to shifting foundations. He wanted to distinguish between true and false, and eventually learned not to accept or believe too firmly in anything in order to free himself from errors. He says he resolved to use the powers of his mind to choose his own paths of understanding.</p>

<p><strong>Part Two:</strong> Works composed from several people are often less perfect than those from one. Architecture by one architect is is usually better than one with several architects. Has anyone considered rebuilding the foundation of of a house or town in order to rebuild it more beautifully? This is what Descartes is trying to do with his thought: throw away everything and rebuild thought that is entirely his own. Before, though, he decides to plan <strong>a method</strong> to get to true knowledge, something with only a <strong>few simple principles</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Accept nothing as true unless it was presented so clearly and so distinctly that I have no doubt about it.</li>
<li>Divide each difficulty that I am examining into as many parts as possible in order to help solve it.</li>
<li>Think orderly, and begin with the simplest and easiest things first, then gradually get to the more complex.</li>
<li>Be so thorough and complete so as to omit nothing.</li>
</ol>


<p>His thought is that, like his understanding of math, there cannot be anything so distant or hidden that one could not eventually discover it.</p>

<p><strong>Part Three:</strong> Descartes decides here to come up with <strong>a few maxims</strong> / moral codes to help him get by while he tears down and rebuilds his thought-castle.</p>

<ol>
<li>Obey the laws and customs of my country and live according to the most moderate opinions and actions of the people.</li>
<li>Be as firm and resolute in my actions as possible.</li>
<li>Attempt to conquer myself rather than fortune and accustom myself to believe that nothing is entirely in my power except my thoughts, that this will lead me to more contentedness, happiness and freedom.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Part four:</strong> This is where Descartes gets into his conclusions, of which he prefaces by saying he&rsquo;s not sure if he should say them since they are so abstract and unusual. He decides to reject everything he previously believed as proofs and to pretend that everything that had ever entered his mind was just a dream. It is here he discovers and concludes the thought: <em>I think therefore I am.</em> He goes on to say since he can imagine that his body does not exist, while still thinking, that the mind must be completely distinct from the body and that the essence of existence is in thinking, not in the material. This gives him some sort of ground for certainty, but he still has doubts. Here he quickly assumes that since he is not perfect, but he can think of something that is perfect, there must be a greater perfection more perfect than him, outside of himself. And since this thought was inside of him, it must have come from somewhere. Something less perfect must have been made by something more perfect, and the idea of perfect must have been given to him. Thus he has just proven the existence of God, and all the things that he saw as imperfect (doubt, inconstancy, sadness etc.) must not exist in this God. This he uses as a basis to say he does have some sturdy ground to rely on, and that if there is some confusion or anything in him, it is only because he is not perfect. Finally, he says that if we are ever confused, we should rely only on our reason, not our senses or imagination.</p>

<blockquote><p>For reason does not dictate that what we see or imagine thus is true, but it does tell us that all our ideas and notions must have some basis in truth, for it would not be possible that God, who is all perfect and true, should have put them in us unless it were so.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Part five:</strong> Here he starts to link the idea of a perfect God with laws of nature. He imagines that if God were to create another world it must operate in the same exact way as ours. He then has a handful of pages that talk about anatomy and blood flow and concludes that the body is like a machine, far better than anything a man has ever created, and thus, something more admirable must have created us. He talks, then, about the distinction between man and animal, how man is far superior to animal, that man has a rational mind and a reasonable soul that animal does not have. He concludes by saying this about the soul:</p>

<blockquote><p>it is of the greatest importance: for, after the error of those who deny the existence of God, which error I think I have sufficiently refuted above, there is nothing which leads feeble minds more readily astray from the straight path of virtue than to imagine that the soul of animals is of the same nature as our own, and that, consequently, we have nothing to fear or to hope for after this life, any more than have flies or ants; instead, when one knows how much they differ, one can understand much better the reasons which prove that our soul is of a nature entirely independent of the body, and that, consequently, it is not subject to die with it; then, since one cannot see other causes for its destruction, one is naturally led to judge from this that it is immortal.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Part six:</strong> Descartes concludes by proposing we move away from speculative philosophy to something more practical. That we can be certain of things and that only with experiment and reason can we make advancements. That we have not even begun to see the kinds of advancements in areas like medicine that could be made. There are simple principles and truths of nature that we can discover and wield and make public for the progress of each man. If anyone has any question or objection, send it to his publisher and he will be interested in replying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 3, An Historical Tour and the Problem of Western Philosophy]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/28/philosophy-of-civilization-pt3.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T08:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/28/philosophy-of-civilization-pt3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a large majority of The Philosophy Of Civilization, Schweitzer gives a bit of a tour of philosophy and history, overviewing some of the major people and periods. He starts with the problem of Western Philosophy, overviews history from the Greeks to the present, their struggle for a world-view, and then gives his new proposal. I won&rsquo;t go over all of his reflections, but I want to give a brief overview to at least setup some basics.</p>

<h2>Western Philosophy&rsquo;s Strength and Weakness</h2>

<p>The strength of Western Philosophy is in it&rsquo;s &ldquo;life-affirmation&rdquo; and it&rsquo;s &ldquo;optimistic-ethical&rdquo; thought. These are two terms Schweitzer uses, amongst many others, throughout the book. Western thought strived to be optimistic, and this, when held onto firmly, is what led society so far—to so much discover, deep thought, and invention.</p>

<blockquote><p>For us Westerners civilization consists in this: that we work simultaneously for the perfecting of ourselves and of the world&hellip; . The history of Western philosophy is the history of the struggle for an optimistic outlook on life. If in antiquity and in modern times the peoples of Europe have managed to produce a civilization, it is because the optimistic world-view was dominant in their thought, and held the pessimistic permanently in subjection, although it was not able to suppress it altogether. (pp. 94-95)</p></blockquote>

<p>Though it&rsquo;s strength of optimism brought it so far, its weakness is that it lacked a sufficient, basic, and thorough world-view to sustain itself. It was searching in the wrong places and attempting to give itself a foundation on unstable ideas. And when it&rsquo;s optimism led it to great achievement, it forgot to reflect upon itself and was wrecked in the results.</p>

<!-- Society became enamored with it's material achievement, with its progress. It rode its optimistic wave and became deceived by its results, infatuated with itself, and lost in it. It's holding to the natural sciences shook its optimism from itself. ..infatuation with the material came to pessimism which it wasn't able to see in itself or reconcile. It neglected to consider the pessimistic thought and resignation of the east—one which ultimately needs to be brought into view to come to a successful world-view (??). Philosophy had essentially lost it's duty—it lost it's reflection and creativity and ability to give meaning to the world. It became mechanical, academic, and an infatuation with it's own past. And throughout history, philosophy never succeeded in building a solid world-view or a single kernel of thought that would carry it through without destroying itself as it had begun to do. -->


<p></p>

<h2>Beginning with the Greeks</h2>

<p>Schweitzer starts with the Greeks who, he says, begin to free themselves from their underlying religion and belief in the gods and move to a world-view based on knowledge and thought.</p>

<p><strong>The sophist</strong> begin criticizing social life, deciding that morals are invented by society for its own interests. The thinking man is to free himself from this and make his own morals based on his pleasure and interests.</p>

<p><strong>Socrates</strong>, Schweitzer says goes only little further than them. <em>&ldquo;In the place of their simply pleasurable he put the rationally pleasurable.&rdquo;</em> His greatness lies in his attempt to ground ground himself in thought, reason, and inner conviction. His downfall is his obsession with the individual&rsquo;s relation to the state as well as, like the other Greeks, his attempt to link his thought with pleasure—that an individual&rsquo;s happiness can be connected to the interests of society.</p>

<blockquote><p>The conception of the rationally pleasurable, which was the legacy of Socrates, is not productive enough to keep a world alive. It is impossible to develop from it the ideas of a utilitarianism directed to the welfare of the community, although he believed he founded them in it. Ethical thought remains confided within the circle of the <em>ego</em>. Every attempt to ennoble the rationally pleasurable ends in life-affirmation changing into life-negation. On this logical fact was wrecked the ancient West, which, after the critical awakening  of the Greek spirit, could have been saved only by means of a reflective optimistic-ethical outlook on life. It was able to take seriously what Socrates gave it, but not to make it capable of producint life and civilization. Plato, too, and Aristotle, the two great independent thinkers of antiquity, are incapable of producing an ethic of action, and so giving civilization a firm foundation. (p. 121)</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>The Stoics</strong> attempt to widen Socrates' narrow vision into something more cosmic. They too though, are too caught up in questions of pleasure and non-pleasure and citizenship to really go beyond. And their difference in an attempt to find a world-view in what Schweitzer calls &ldquo;nature-philosophy&rdquo; only leads to resignation (I&rsquo;ll get back to this idea in a later post).</p>

<blockquote><p>Nature-philosophy only provides the cosmic background for the resignation to which ethics have come&hellip; . It is true that there is power in the preaching of resignation which ancient thought, no longer ignorant about life, allows to go forth to mankind. Resignation is the lofty porch through which one enters upon ethics. But Epicurus and the Stoics stay on in this porch. Resignation becomes for them an ethiacal world-view. Hence they are incapable of leading ancient society from its ingenuous life-and-world-affirmation to a philosophy based on thought. (p. 121)</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Plato</strong> attempts to ground the Good on something more absolute in his forms, which Schweitzer says is devoid of content, supra-ethical, and dualistic. His virtues are the only practical element in his philosophy but have nothing to do with his conception of Good in his supra-ethical and immaterial world.</p>

<blockquote><p>The true ethic, then, is world-negation. To this view Plato was committed the moment he allowed the ethical to find its home in the world of pure Being. Thoughts of ascetic inactivity find expression in him side by side with the Greek feeling for reality, and it is confusing that he does not recognize the conflict between them, but speaks now in one sense, now in the other. His ethic is a chaos, and he himself an expert in inconsistency. Plato&rsquo;s ethic of world-negation is not an original creation; he takes it over in the Indian setting in which it is offered to him by Orphism and Pythagoreanism. By what route there found its way into Greek thought this pessimism which had been thought out to a system and equipped with the doctrine of re-incarnation, we do not know, and shall probably never learn&hellip; . (p. 123)</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;ve heard different people comment on this dualism in Plato but when I had originally read him I didn&rsquo;t see it that way. I&rsquo;ll have to keep that in mind next time I read him&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Aristotle</strong>, Schweitzer says, attempts to make ethics more actionable, grounded in rational reflection and virtue acquired by practice. And though he finds something simple and practical, Schweitzer says it is valueless in itself as it attempts to come to conclusions without understanding itself.</p>

<blockquote><p>Aristotle is so firmly resolved not to have anything to do with the problem of the basic principle of ethics, that he will allow nothing to lead him to discuss it. He means to voyage along the coast, keep to facts, and deal with ethics as if they were a branch of natural science&hellip; .</p>

<p>It is because he misunderstands their nature that Aristotle cannot help ethics forward. Plato goes beyond Socrates and loses himself in abstractions. Aristotle, in order to maintain the connection with reality, aims lower than Socrates. He brings together material for a monumental building, and runs up a wooden shack. Among teachers of virtue he is one of the greatest. Nevertheless, the least of those who venture on the search for the basic principle of the ethical is greater than he. (p. 127)</p></blockquote>

<p>Schweitzer continues to reflect upon these and others, and he ends with the Greeks by concluding that they were unable to find something grounded to progress humanity. It was only with the later Greek thinkers that begin to find something more &ldquo;optimistic-ethical&rdquo; that would progress humanity, but they were too late.</p>

<blockquote><p>The optimistic-ethical monism of the later Stoics is like a sunbeam breaking through in the evening of the long, gloomy day of antiquity while the darkness of the middle ages is already drawing on, but it has no power to waken any civilization to life. The time for that is past. The spirit of antiquity, having failed to reach an ethical nature-philosophy, has become the prey of a pessimistic dualism in which no ethic of action is any longer possible; there can only be an ethic of purification.</p>

<p>The thoughts of Seneca, Epictetus, and Marcus Aurelius are the winter seeds of a coming civilization. (p. 140)</p></blockquote>

<h2>Rennaissance and Post-Rennaissance</h2>

<p>From the Greeks, Schweitzer moves to the Renaissance where he speaks of a new world-and-life-affirmation which breaks through as never before. This time begins to move towards nature and discovery, asking questions about governing laws and the universe and making them serviceable to itself. This new phase came quickly, Schweitzer says, but without much fruit. It had become optimistic, not because of a new deepened thought, but because its understanding of the world gave it power.</p>

<blockquote><p>[B]eginning at the end of the fourteenth century, and it arises as a protest against the medieval enslavement of the human spirit. The movement is helped to victory by the increasing knowledge of Greek Philosophy in its original form, which is the result of the migration to Italy about the middle of the fifteenth century of learned Greeks from Constantinople. Among the thinking men of that time there arises the believe that philosophy must be something more elemental and more living than Scholasticism taught.</p>

<p>But the thought of antiquity would not have been sufficient by itself to keep alive this new world-and-life-affirmation which appealed to it as a precedent. It had not, in truth, the mentality required. (p. 141)</p></blockquote>

<p>One interesting characteristic Schweitzer makes here is a transformation of pessimism to optimism, with the help of Christianity. Christianity&rsquo;s transformation, he says, is the decisive event of this the modern age.</p>

<blockquote><p>Under the steadily active influence of the new mentality, the world-view of Christianity changes, and becomes leavened with the yeast of the world-and-life-affirmation. It gradually begins to be accepted as self-evident that the spirit of Jesus does not renounce the world, but aims at transforming it. The early Christian concept of the Kingdom of God, which was born of pessimism and, thanks to Augustine, prevailed through the Middle Ages, is rendered impotent, and its place is taken by a conception which is the offspring of modern optimism&hellip; . During this period Christianity takes no account of what is happening to itself. It believes that it is remaining unaltered, whereas in reality, by this change from pessimism to optimism, it is surrendering its original character. (p. 143)</p></blockquote>

<p>Though post Reformation thought would view Jesus' teaching as an active action to transform the world, Schweitzer says it was not so—it is the paradox of his teaching that he had an active ethical teaching combined with an awaiting of the end of the world. The modern age overlooked this paradox and held to the optimism of his teaching, and combined it, he says, with the late stoicism of a rational and active ethic. Where they were once unable to come together because of these differing viewpoints, they now were able to because of a new bridge between their world-views.</p>

<p>The combination of this Stoic and Christian ethic with the achievements of discovery and invention brought a belief in progress which brought forth this new age. But as time went on, progress would begin to leave ethics behind until it brings ethics down with it. And this begins a great turning point having gone from pessimism to optimism, now it returns to pessimism again.</p>

<blockquote><p>But as the cart gets heavier and the road more difficult, so that ethics ought to lend their strength to help, they refuse, because they have no strength of their own. The cart begins to run backward, and carries belief in progress, and ethics with it, down the hill.</p>

<p>The task before philosophy was to change the world-and-life-affirmation which arose from enthusiasm over the attainments of discovery and invention into a deeper, inner world-and-life-affirmation arising out of thought about the universe and the life of man, and on that same foundation to build up an ethical system. But philosophy could do neither.</p>

<p>About the middle of the nineteenth century, when it has become perfectly clear that we are living with a world-and-life-affirmation which has its source merely in our confidence in discovery and invention and not in any profounder thought about the world and life, our fate is sealed. The modern optimistic-ethical world-view, after doing so much for the material development of civilization, has to collapse like a building erected already to a considerable height but on rotten foundations. (p. 149)</p></blockquote>

<h2>Ethics in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries</h2>

<p>These two centuries begin to go back to similar questions posed by the Greeks by asking how the self can be merged with altruism, or society as a whole. Many had attempted to put it under rational thought and argued that if an individual truly understands his own interests, he would connect them with the interests of society. Others had continued that thought and concluded that individuals left alone would only go towards their selfish desires, and authority had to compel them to do otherwise, by appealing to their egoism and material desires. Individuals could be could be regulated by society itself by using praise and blame. Hume had even apparently encouraged the love of fame, as it would keep one in the spotlight of others and encourage one to please them.</p>

<p>And against the more utilitarian viewpoints, others had proposed that morality is really the striving for perfection given to us by nature. There seemed to be a swirl of rational thought attempting to grasp something to build a society for the benefit of all its members, but Schweitzer points out as he does with the Greeks, that these thoughts end in resignation.</p>

<blockquote><p>The consideration, therefore, that egoism, rightly understood, will oblige the individual to resolve on activity which is directed to promoting the common good, is a ship which sails well, but leaks. (p. 152)</p>

<p>Ethical thought falls from one paradox into another. If, as in antiquity, it thinks out a system in which the activity that must be directed to the common good is not sufficiently represented, it arrives at ethics which are no longer ethics, and ends in resignation. If it assumes and starts from such an activity directed to the common good, it arrives at an ethic in which there is no ethical personality. Strange to say, it is unable to mark out the middle course and let an activity which is directed to the promotion of the common good spring from the ethical personality itself. (p. 158)</p></blockquote>

<p>Schweitzer begins here to point more towards his proposal that the ethical cannot be supported by rational thought alone, and especially not by attempting to merge spiritual happiness with material happiness. Maybe it could stand alone by an inner compulsion. Of this age he ends with a guy named Anthony Ashley-Cooper (aka Earl Shaftesbury) who became a major influence to the next generations, returning them back to the creative spirit of the Renaissance. About him Schweitzer says,</p>

<blockquote><p>he places its origin in feeling&hellip; . [T]he important thing is that he puts forward a living philosophy of nature in combination with ethics. He is convinced that harmony reigns in the universe and that man is meant to experience this harmony in himself. Aesthetic feeling and ethical thinking are for him forms of union with that divine life which struggles to find expression in the spiritual being of man as it does with nature. With Shaftesbury ethics descends from a rocky mountain range into a luxuriant plain. The utilitarians as yet know nothing of a world. Their ethic is restricted to considerations about the relation of the individual to society. The anti-utilitarians have some idea of a world, but not a correct one. They elaborate ethics with a formal theology and a formal philosophizing about the All, but Shaftesbury plants ethical thought in the universe of reality, which he himself contemplates through an idealising optimism, reaching thereby a direct and universal notion of the moral.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Rationalism and beyond</h2>

<p>With a rational and optimistic grounding and a strong belief in progress, society began to make great advancements, not only materially but through the beginning of tolerance, the end of witch trials and superstitious thought, torture becoming less and less used, and new ideals of all becoming educated. &ldquo;The war against ignorance is begun,&rdquo; Schweitzer says. A wave of enthusiasm from the previous generations was rode, but not for too long before people began to become critical of it, and Napoleon wreaked havoc on Europe, putting it &ldquo;in a condition of misery.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>The ethical and the optimistic come into power, therefore, in the philosophy of the eighteenth century, although they have not yet received any real foundation. Scepticism and materialism range around the fortress like hordes of unconquered enemies, thought at first without being dangerous; as a rule they have themselves absorbed no small amount of belief-in-progress and of ethical enthusiasm.  (pp. 167-168)</p></blockquote>

<p>Moving into the nineteenth century, society kept progressing, but it began to leave ethics behind. The sciences, biology and Darwinian thought began to mark their influence as society moved from the rational to the actual. Philosophy became mere academic review and it&rsquo;s creativity began to vanish. Questions of individual ethics became no longer interesting, progress no longer appreciated, and the conviction of the previous generations began to fade. And with this, the optimism western society once held became dull, the excitement of discovery gone, and only cold hard facts remained and the utility of every person sought after.</p>

<blockquote><p>When, at the close of the eighteenth century and the beginning of the nineteenth, the reaction against rationalism set in and criticism began to play upon it, its optimism was reproached as superficial and its ethics as sentimental. But the spiritual movements which criticize it and take its place cannot develop on the same lines what it accomplished, in spite of its manifold imperfections, by inspiring men with ideals of civilization grounded in reason. The energy of thought about civilization dwindles imperceptibly but steadily. In proportion as the world-view of rationalism is left behind, the feeling for actuality makes its influence felt, until at last, from the middle of the nineteenth century onwards, ideals are borrowed no longer from reason but from actuality, and we therewith sink still further into a state of uncivilization and lack of humanity. This is the clearest and most important of all the facts which can be established in the history of our civilization. (p. 91)</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 2, Crisis]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/06/philosophy-of-civilization-pt2.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T18:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/03/06/philosophy-of-civilization-pt2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Albert Schweitzer" title="Albert Schweitzer's Philosophy of Civilization (1924)" src="/assets/images/albert_schweitzer_philosophy_of_civilization.jpg" class="alignleft" /></p>

<blockquote><p>We are living today under the sign of the collapse of civilization. The situation has not been produced by the war; the latter is only a manifestation of it. The spiritual atmosphere has solidified into actual facts, which again react on it with disastrous results in every respect&hellip; . It is clear now to everyone that the suicide of civilization is in progress. What yet remains of it is no longer safe. It is still standing, indeed, because it was not exposed to the destructive pressure which overwhelmed the rest, but, like the rest, it is built upon rubble, and the next landslide will very likely carry it away.</p></blockquote>

<p>Wow&hellip; It is fascinating to look back and learn about how society viewed itself and the world. It was 1923 when he published this book, between both world wars, which gives you an idea where he&rsquo;s coming from. There seemed to be an obsession in the air for progress, for achievement. Imperialism, the white man&rsquo;s burden, over industrialization, survival of the fittest, social utilitarianism, social Darwinism, human zoos. The ideals and ideas seemed to trump the value of life. Schweitzer is attempting to grapple with and reflect on the state of society. What led it here? What can we learn from history? What does true civilization look like? Is there a way out?</p>

<blockquote><p>We want to get into our hands the key of the secret, so that we may with it unlock the new age, the age in which the worn out becomes again unworn and the spiritual and ethical can no longer get worn out. We must study the history of civilization otherwise than as our predecessors did, or we shall be finally lost.</p></blockquote>

<p>Ultimately he finds that society is and must be ethical, that it lacks a world view, and must find one that is simple, optimistic, and upholds the value of all life.</p>

<blockquote><p>Entering on the question as to what is the real essential nature of civilization, I come to the pronouncement that this is ultimately ethical. I know that in thus stating the problem as a moral one I shall surprise and even disgust the spirit of our times, which is accustomed to move amidst aesthetic, historical and material considerations. I imagine, however, that I am myself enough of an artist and also of an historian to be able to comprehend the aesthetic and historical elements in civilization, and that, as a modern physician and surgeon, I am sufficiently modern to appreciate the glamour of the technical and material attainments of our age&hellip; .</p>

<p>Only when we are able to attribute a real meaning to the world and to life shall we be able to also give ourselves to such actions as will produce results of real value. As long as we look on our existence in the world as meaningless, there is no point whatever in desiring to effect anything in the world&hellip; .</p></blockquote>

<p>In the next few posts I&rsquo;ll be going over a few of the main points I&rsquo;ve gathered throughout the book, his reflections on society and philosophy, and his solution.</p>

<blockquote><p>I do not know how how many, or how few, will allow themselves to be persuaded to travel with me on the road indicted above. What I desire above all things—and this is the crux of the whole affair—is that we should all recognize fully that our present entire lack of any theory of the universe is the ultimate source of all the catastrophes and misery of our times, and that we should work together for a theory of the universe and of life, in order that thus we may arrive at a mental disposition which shall make us really and truly civilized men.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Philosophy of Civilization: Pt 1, Albert Schweitzer]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt1.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T11:23:00Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/24/philosophy-of-civilization-pt1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img alt="Albert Schweitzer" title="Albert Schweitzer (1875-1965)" src="/assets/images/Albert_Schweitzer_1952.jpg" class="alignleft" />
I wanted to start off by reviewing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Schweitzer">Albert Schweitzer&rsquo;s</a> book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Philosophy-Civilization-Albert-Schweitzer/dp/0879754036">The Philosophy of Civilization</a>. I&rsquo;ve grown to really admire him as a person and this book is easily one of my all time favorite books. It&rsquo;s written so elegantly, so in depth, and still is so profound and simple. He gives one of the most engaging and practical overviews of history and philosophy that I have ever read. And his ethic—"reverence for life"—is one that I love, and connect with. The basic message of the book is something I think everyone should be exposed to.</p>

<p>Before getting into the book though, I first want to share a little about Schweitzer. Besides noting his lovely hair and mustache, for starters, he is one of the more remarkable people I&rsquo;ve read about. I had primarily known him for his work on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/quest-historical-Jesus-critical-progress-ebook/dp/B00CE1PB1Q/">Jesus</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mysticism-Apostle-Albert-Schweitzer-Library/dp/0801860989">Paul</a>. But he was also a teacher, a pastor, a music scholar—he wrote a 400 page book on Bach in his spare time in French (apparently while teaching <em>and</em> in school for his medical doctorate, and later completely rewrote it&hellip; making it 800 pages&hellip; in German&hellip; because simply translating it wouldn&rsquo;t have sufficed&hellip; he apparently wanted to re-saturate himself with the content to let it sit—authentically—in the German language). He studied medicine for about 6 years, and afterwards became a doctor in Africa, dedicating the rest of his life to serve humanity (I&rsquo;m not sure how he accomplished all he did in his lifetime and kept his sanity). In his autobiography he writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>The plan which I meant now to put into execution had been in my mind for a long time, having been conceived so long ago as my student days. It struck me as incomprehensible that I should be allowed to lead such a happy life, while I saw so many people around me wrestling with care and suffering. Even at school I had felt stirred whenever I got a glimpse of the miserable home surroundings of some of my schoolfellows and compared them with the absolutely ideal conditions in which we children of the parsonage at Günsbach lived. While at the university and enjoying the happiness of being able to study and even to produce some results in science and art, I could not help thinking continually of others who were denied that happiness by their material circumstances or their health. Then one brilliant summer morning at Günsbach, during the Whitesuntide holidays—it was in 1896—there came to me, as I awoke, the thought that I must not accept this happiness as a matter of course, but must give something in return for it. Proceeding to think the matter out at once with calm deliberation, while the birds were singing outside, I settled with myself before I got up, that I would consider myself justified in living till I was thirty for science and art, in order to devote myself from that time forward to the direct service of humanity. Many a time already had I tried to settle what meaning lay hidden for me in the saying of Jesus! &ldquo;Whosoever would save his life shall lose it, and whosoever shall lose his life for My sake and the Gospels shall save it.&rdquo; Now the answer was found. In addition to the outward, I now had inward happiness."</p>

<p>What would be the character of the activities thus planned for the future was not yet clear to me. I left it to circumstances to guide me. One thing only was certain, that it must be directly human service, however inconspicuous the sphere of it.</p></blockquote>

<p>I really got drawn to Schweitzer after reading a small book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Albert-Schweitzers-friendship-Erica-Anderson/dp/B00005VBZH/">Albert Schweitzer&rsquo;s Gift of Friendship</a>, by Erica Anderson. She had befriended him through wanting to film a documentary about him (which she was eventually able to do, after much reluctance by him—she found out after asking him that he once said to another who requested, &ldquo;I would rather burn in hell than have a film made of my life&rdquo;). The film won an academy award for best documentary in 1952. In her book, she writes about her entire experience with him, from the first letters she wrote him, to meeting him for the first time, and her times with him over the years. Her book and documentary give a very personal insight into his life, his humor, and his character and personality, one you wouldn&rsquo;t be able to get by reading his autobiography. He has a unique blend of compassion, intellect, purpose and humor. I could share a bunch of quotes and moments from her book, but for now I want to end with a quote from the documentary she filmed. Schweitzer shares a moment from his childhood:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was hard for me to keep my mind on my studies when my eyes were always wandering outside to the wonders of nature itself&hellip;.  At the age of 9, my life took a new turn. Every morning and evening, I walked nearly two miles over the hills to the school where my parents decided to send me. I was delighted to take these walks by myself&hellip; to think my own thoughts. How well I came to know the changing seasons. But the sheer youthful joy of being alive was something I never knew. I think this is true of many children who appear outwardly care free and content. As far back as I can remember, I was shocked by the suffering I observed in nature. Suffering brought about by the relentless struggle for existence. Still more shocking to me was the pain and mystery inflicted on dumb helpless animals, by the negligence and thoughtlessness of man. Even before I started to go to school, I couldn&rsquo;t understand why I was only expected to pray for human beings when I said my prayers at night. So when my mother had drawn the shudders, and blown out the candle, and kissed me goodnight I secretly said another prayer for all that had life. A prayer that I had made up myself. &ldquo;Dear God, protect and bless all living creatures. Keep them from evil. And let them sleep in peace.&rdquo;</p>

<p>An experience I had during these years made a lasting impression on me. A neighbor&rsquo;s son and I had made slingshots from rubber bands. One Sunday morning he said to me, &ldquo;Come on, let&rsquo;s go up the mountain and shoot birds. This seemed a horrible idea, but I didn&rsquo;t dare object for fear of being laughed at. The birds were singing sweetly in the morning sunshine, so unafraid of us. Crouching like an indian, my friend put a stone in his slingshot and took aim. Obeying his look of command, I did the same, with acute pains of conscience. At that moment the sounds of church bells began to mingle with the sunshine and the birds' song. To me, it was a voice from heaven. I frightened away the birds, to protect them from my friend&rsquo;s shot, and ran home. Ever since, when morning bells ring out in the sunshine, I gratefully remember those bells. For they rang into my heart the commandment, "thought shalt not kill.&rdquo; The matter in which this commandment speaks against killing and cruelty, worked upon me was the great experience of my childhood and youth. Gradually I came to the unshakeable conviction, that we may bring death and pain to a fellow creature only on the compulsion of absolute necessity, and that we must all feel the horror of causing suffering and death by thoughtlessness. I became more and more certain that all of us feel this way, but do not dare to affirm it. We are afraid of being ridiculed as sentimental. We allow ourselves to become callous.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<p>And, if you&rsquo;re interested in a few fun quotes from Erica&rsquo;s book:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/a6f3e4dc-6aa8-4eaa-b1ca-a4f59409aa1e?locale=en" target="_blank">On Erica&rsquo;s first visit</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/8e8d1818-79a4-4ab8-a7cb-a9ee86932d08?locale=en" target="_blank">I used to be lazy as a boy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/ed9c8b96-f585-48ce-b482-ff236d1a6ff2?locale=en" target="_blank">What&rsquo;s honor?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/6af4ffe4-41b8-49ec-92fc-da5552816a01?locale=en" target="_blank">They pick up man Schweitzer assumes needs a ride</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.evernote.com/pub/view/wejrowski/bw-quotes/8b14c990-cadc-4a91-a441-efe63f16d5a6?locale=en" target="_blank">On his routine</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baby Reincarnation]]></title>
    <link href="http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/20/welcome.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T19:33:28Z</updated>
    <id>http://brentwejrowski.com/2014/02/20/welcome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello world. A new born baby has arrived, delivered from that flying baby stork&hellip; not a human baby though&hellip; a website baby&hellip; it&rsquo;s the fifth reincarnation of this website. We&rsquo;ll see where this baby takes us. For now it will take it&rsquo;s form as an outlet for the interesting reads I find in front of my eyeballs. A place to gather my thoughts and attempt to understand them by writing about them and sharing. As a personal project, I&rsquo;m planning on reading a new book from a major philosopher each month for the next year, and then hopefully summarizing each as I go. So I&rsquo;ll start out by summarizing a few past reads and I&rsquo;ll go from there, probably sprinkling in some others along the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
